<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The description of a voyage made by certaine ships of Holland into the East Indies VVith their aduentures and successe: together with the description of the countries, townes, and inhabitantes of the same: who set forth on the second of Aprill 1595. and returned on the 14. of August. 1597. Translated out of Dutch into English by W.P.</title>
            <title>Verhael vande reyse by de Hollandtsche schepen gedaen naer Oost Indien. English.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1598</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 129 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 43 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A05051</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 15193</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S109348</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99844998</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99844998</idno>
            <idno type="VID">9867</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A05051)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 9867)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 256:01)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The description of a voyage made by certaine ships of Holland into the East Indies VVith their aduentures and successe: together with the description of the countries, townes, and inhabitantes of the same: who set forth on the second of Aprill 1595. and returned on the 14. of August. 1597. Translated out of Dutch into English by W.P.</title>
                  <title>Verhael vande reyse by de Hollandtsche schepen gedaen naer Oost Indien. English.</title>
                  <author>Phillip, William.</author>
                  <author>Houtman, Cornelis de, d. 1599, attributed name.</author>
                  <author>Langenes, Barent.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 40 leaves : ill. (woodcuts), maps  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted by [John Windet? for] Iohn Wolfe,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1598.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Sometimes attributed to Cornelius de Houtman, who was commander of the voyage.</note>
                  <note>A translation of: Verhael vande reyse by de Hollandtsche schepen gedaen naer Oost Indiennez.</note>
                  <note>Translator's dedication signed: W. Phillip.</note>
                  <note>Foreword signed by the publisher of the Dutch edition: Bernardt Langhenez.</note>
                  <note>Actual printer's name conjectured by STC.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The foure Hollanders ships voyage.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Java (Indonesia) --  Description and travel --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:9867:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:9867:1"/>
            <p>THE DESCRIPTION of a voyage made by certaine Ships of Holland into
the Eaſt INDIES. With their aduentures and ſucceſſe: Together With the
deſcription of the Countries, Townes, and inhabitantes of the ſame: Who
ſet forth on the ſecond of Aprill 1595. and returned on the 14. of
Auguſt. <hi>1597.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Tranſlated out of Dutch into Engliſh by W. P.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>depiction of a ship</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>LONDON Imprinted by <hi>Iohn Wolfe.</hi> 1598.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:9867:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:9867:2"/>
            <head>To the right worſhipfull Sir <hi>James Scudamore,
Knight.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight worſhipfull, this ſmall trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie (written in Dutch,
ſhewing a late voyage performed by certain <hi>Hollanders</hi> to the
Iſlandes of <hi>Iaua,</hi> part of the Eaſt <hi>Indies</hi>) falling into
my handes, and in my iudgement deſeruing no leſſe commendati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on then
thoſe of our Countrey men, (as Captaine <hi>Raimond</hi> in the
<hi>Penelope,</hi> Maiſter <hi>Foxcroft</hi> in the <hi>Marchant Royall,</hi>
and M. <hi>Iames Lanca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> in the <hi>Edward Bonauenture,</hi> vnto the
ſaid Eaſt <hi>Indies,</hi> by the Cape <hi>de Bona Sperance,</hi> in
<hi>Anno 1591.</hi> as alſo M. <hi>Iohn Newbery,</hi> and <hi>Raphael
Fich</hi> ouer land through <hi>Siria</hi> from <hi>Aleppo</hi> vnto
<hi>Ormus</hi> and <hi>Goa,</hi> and by the ſaid <hi>Rapha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el Fich</hi>
himſelfe to <hi>Bengala, Malacca, Pegu,</hi> and other places in <hi>Anno
1583.</hi> as at large appeareth in a booke written by M. <hi>Richard
Haclute</hi> a Gentleman very ſtudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous therein, &amp; entituled the
Engliſh voyages) I thought it not vnconuenient to tranſlate the ſame into
our mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther tongue, thereby to procure more light and encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement to ſuch
as are deſirous to trauell thoſe Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, for the common wealth and
commoditie of this Realme and themſelues. And knowing that all men are 
<pb facs="tcp:9867:3"/> not like affected, I was ſo bold to ſhrowd it vnder your
worſhips protection, as being aſſured of your good di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoſition to
the fauouring of trauell and trauellers, (and whereby it hath pleaſed God to
aduance you to that honourable title, which at this preſent you beare) and
ſo not fitter for the protection of any then your ſelfe: and as a poore
friend wiſhing all happines and proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity in all your valiant actions.
Which if it pleaſe your worſhippe to like and accept, it may procure the
pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding in a more large and ample diſcourſe of an Eaſt
<hi>Indian</hi> voyage, lately performed and ſet forth by one <hi>Iohn
Hughen</hi> of <hi>Linſchoten,</hi> to your further delight. Wherewith
crauing your fauor, &amp; beſeeching God to bleſſe your worſhip, with
my good Ladie your wife, I moſt humbly take my leaue:</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>This 16. of <hi>Ianuarie.
1597.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline> 
               <signed>Your Worſhips to commaunde <hi>W.
Phillip.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:9867:3"/>
            <head>To the Bayliefes, Burghemaiſters, &amp; Counſell of the
Towne of Middelborgh in <hi>Zeelande.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T may well bee thought (Right wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipfull) as many learned
men are of opinion, that the actions and aduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of the ancients long
ſince done &amp; performed, haue beene ſet forth with more ſhow of wonder
and ſtrangeneſſe then they in truth deſerued: the reaſon as I think
was, becauſe that in thoſe daies there were many lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and wiſe men,
who in their writings ſought by all meanes they could to excell each other,
touching the deſcription of Countries &amp; nations: And againe to the
contrarie, for want of good Hiſtoriographers and writers, many famous actes
and trauels of diuers nations and Countries lie hidden, and in a manner buried
vnder ground, as wholly forgotten and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne, vnleſſe it were ſuch as
the Grecians and Romanes for their owne glories and aduantages thought good to
declare. But to come to the matter of voyages by ſea, it is euident to all
the world, what voyage <hi>Iaſon</hi> with certaine yong Grecian Princes made
to <hi>Colchos</hi> in the Oriental Countries to winne the golden Fleece, as
alſo the trauels by <hi>Hercules</hi> performed into <hi>Libia</hi> in the
Weſt partes, to winne the <hi>Aurea Mala</hi> or golden apples of
<hi>Heſperides,</hi> which notwithſtanding neither for length, daunger, nor
profite, are any thing comparable to the nauigations and voyages, that of late
within the ſpace of <pb facs="tcp:9867:4"/> one hundreth years haue been performed &amp;
made into the Eaſt &amp; Weſt Indies, whereby in a manner there is not one
hauen on the ſea coaſt, nor any point of land in the whole world, but hath
in time beene ſought and founde out. I will not at this preſent diſpute
or make an argument, whether the Countries and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of late yeares found
out and diſcouered, were knowne to the auncients, but this is most certaine,
that not any ſtrange worke or aduenture was, or euer ſhall be performed,
but by the ſpeciall grace, fauour and mightie hand of God, and that ſuch
are worthy perpetual memory, as with noble minds haue ſought to effect, and
be the firſt enterpriſers thereof, and with moſt valiant courages and
wiſedomes, haue performed ſuch long &amp; dangerous voyages into the Eaſt
and Weſt Indies, as alſo ſuch Kinges and Princes, as with their Princely
liberalities haue imployed their treaſures, ſhippes, men and munitions to
the furtherance and performance of ſo worthy actes, which not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding
in the end turned to their great aduancementes and inriching with great
treaſures, which by thoſe meanes they haue drawn, &amp; cauſed in great
aboundance to be brought from thence, in ſuch manner, that the King of
<hi>Spaine</hi> nowe liuing, (hauing both the Indies in his poſſeſsion,
&amp; reaping the abundant treaſures which yearly are brought out of thoſe
coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries) hath not only (although couertly) ſought all the means he could
to bring all Chriſtendome vnder his dominion, but alſo (that which no King
or country whatſoeuer although of grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter might then he hath euer done) hee
is not aſhamed to vſe this poſie, <hi>Necſpe, nec metu.</hi> And
although the firſt foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders and diſcouerers of thoſe Countries haue
alwayes ſought to hinder and intercept other nations from hauing any part of
their glorie, yet hereby all nations, &amp; indifferent perſons may well know
and perceiue the ſpeciall policie, and valour of theſe vnited Prouinces, in
trauelling into both the Indies, in the <pb facs="tcp:9867:4"/> faces, &amp; to the great
griefe of their many and mighty enemies. Wherby it is to be hoped, that if they
continue in their enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſes begun, they will not onely draw the moſt
part of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian treaſures into theſe Countries, but thereby
diſinherite &amp; ſpoyle the Countrie of <hi>Spayne</hi> of her principall
reuenewes, and treaſures of marchandiſes and trafiques, which ſhe
continually vſeth and receyueth out of theſe countries, and out of
<hi>Spayne</hi> are ſent into the Indies, and ſo put the King of
<hi>Spaine</hi> himſelfe in minde of his fooliſh deuiſe which hee vſeth
for a poſie tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the new world, which is, <hi>Non ſufficit orbis,</hi>
like a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond <hi>Alexander magnus,</hi> deſiring to rule ouer all the
world, as it is manifestly knowne. And becauſe this diſcription is fallen
into my handes, wherein is contayned the firſt voyage of the Low-country men
into the Eaſt Indies, with the aduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures happened vnto them, ſet downe
and iuſtified by ſuch as were preſent in the voyage, I thought it good to
put it in print, with many pictures and cardes, whereby the reader may the
eaſilier perceyue and diſcerne, the natures, apparels, and faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of
thoſe Countries and people, as alſo the manner of their ſhippes, together
with the fruitfulneſſe and great aboundance of the ſame, hoping that this
my labour will not onely be accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table vnto all Marchants and Saylers, which
hereafter meane to traffique into thoſe Countries, but alſo pleaſant and
profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to all ſuch as are deſirous to looke into ſo newe and
ſtrange things, which neuer heretofore were knowne vnto our nation. And
againe for that all hiſtories haue their particular commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditie, (ſpecially
ſuch as are collected and gathered together) not by common report, from the
firſt, ſeconde, or thirde man, but by ſuch as haue ſeene and beene
preſent in the actions, and that are liuing to iuſtifie and verifie the
ſame: And although eloquence and words well placed in ſhewing a hiſtory,
are great ornamentes and beautifyinges to the ſame, yet ſuch reports &amp; 
<pb facs="tcp:9867:5"/> declarations are much more worthy credite, &amp; commendabler for
the benefit of the commonwealth, which are not ſet down or diſciphered by
ſubtill eloquence, but ſhowne and performed by ſimple plaine men, ſuch
as by copiouſneſſe of wordes, or ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiltie do not alter or chaunge the
matter from the truth there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, which at this day is a common and notorious
fault in many Hiſtoriographers: And thinking with my ſelfe to whome I were
beſt to dedicate the ſame, I found it not fitter for any then for the right
worſhipfull Gouernours of this famous Towne of <hi>Middelborgh,</hi> wherein
for the ſpace of 19. yeares I haue peaceably continued, ſpecially becauſe
your worſhips do not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deale with great ſtore of ſhipping, and
matter belonging to nauigation, but are alſo well pleaſed to heare, and
great fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therers to aduance both ſhipping and traffiques, wherein
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth not onely the welfare of all marchants, inhabitants, and
cittizens of this famous City, but alſo of all the common wealth of the
vnited Prouinces, hoping your worſhips wil not onely ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept this my labour,
but protect &amp; warrantiſe the ſame againſt all men: Wherwith I
beſeech God to bleſſe you with wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and godly policie, to gouerne
the Common wealth: <hi>Middleborgh</hi> this 19 of October. 1597.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your worſhips ſeruant to command <hi>Bernardt
Langhenez.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <head>
            <pb facs="tcp:9867:5"/> A briefe diſcription of a voyage per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed <hi>by
certaine Hollanders to &amp;</hi> from the Eaſt INDIES, with their
aduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures and ſucceſſe.</head>
         <div type="section">
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He ancient Hiſtoriographers and diſcribers of the world haue
much commended, and at large with great prayſe ſet downe the diuers and
ſeuerall voyages of many no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble &amp; valiant Captains (as of <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander
Magnus, Seleucus, Antiochus, Patrocles, Oneſecritus</hi>) into the Eaſt
<hi>Indies,</hi> which not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding haue not ſet downe a great part of
thoſe coontries, as not being as then diſcouered, whereby it is thought and
iudged by ſome men, that <hi>India</hi> is the full third part of all the
world, becauſe of the great Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinces, mighty Citties, famous and Iſlands
(full of coſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly marchandiſes, and treaſures from thence brought into all
partes of the worlde) that are therein: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the auncient writers were very
curious, and yet not ſo much as men in our age: They had ſome know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
thereof, but altogether vncertaine, but we at this day are fully certified
therein, both touching the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, townes, ſtreames and hauens, with the
trafiques therein vſed and frequented, whereby all the world, ſo farre
diſtant and ſeperated from thoſe ſtrange nations, are by trade of
marchandiſes vnited therevnto, &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by commonly knowne vnto them: The
Portingalles firſt began to enterpriſe the voyage, who by art of
na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uigation (in our time much more experienced &amp; grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then in times
paſt, and therefore eaſilier performed) <pb facs="tcp:9867:6"/> diſcouered thoſe
wild Countries of <hi>India,</hi> therein pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curing great honour to their
King, making his name fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous, and bringing a ſpeciall and great profite of
all kindes of ſpices into their Countrie, which thereby is ſpread
throughout all the worlde, yet that ſufficed not, for that the Engliſhmen
(not inferiour to any nation in the world for arte of nauigation) haue
likewiſe vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken the Indian voyage, and by their ſaid voyages into
thoſe Countries, made the ſame commonly knowne vnto their Country, wherein
Sir <hi>Fraunces Drake,</hi> and M. <hi>Candiſh</hi> are chiefly to bee
commended, who not onely ſayled into the Eaſt <hi>Indies,</hi> but alſo
rounde about the world, with moſt proſperous voyages, by which their
voyages, ours haue beene furthered and ſet forwarde, for that the condition
of the <hi>Indies</hi> is, that the more it is ſayled into, the more it is
diſcouered, by ſuch as ſayle the ſame, ſo ſtrange a Countrey it is:
So that beſides the famous voyages of the Countries aforeſaid, in the ende
certain people came into <hi>Holland</hi> (a nation wel known) certifying them,
that they might eaſily prepare certaine ſhippes to ſayle into the Eaſt
<hi>Indies,</hi> there to traffique &amp; buy ſpyces, &amp;c. By ſayling
ſtraight from <hi>Hollande</hi> and alſo from other countries bordering
about it, with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to ſee ſtrange and rich wares of other Countries,
&amp; that ſhould not be brought vnto them by ſtrangers, but by their owne
countrey men, which ſome men would eſteeme to be impoſſible,
conſidering the long voyage and the daungers thereof, together with the
vnaccuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med ſaylinges and little knowledge thereof by ſuch as neuer
ſayled that way, and rather eſteeme it madneſſe, then any point of
wiſedome, and folly rather then good conſideration. But notwithſtanding
wee haue ſeene <pb n="2" facs="tcp:9867:6"/> foure ſhips make that voyage, who after
many dangers hauing performed their voyage, returned againe and haue brought
with them thoſe wares, that would neuer haue beene thought coulde haue beene
brought into theſe countries by any <hi>Holland</hi> ſhips; but what
ſhoulde I herein moſt commende eyther the willingneſſe and good
performance of the parties, or the happineſſe of their voyage? whereof that
I may giue the reader ſome knowledge, I will ſhew what I haue hearde and
beene informed of, concerning the deſcription of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, cuſtomes,
and manners of the nations, by them in this voyage ſeene &amp; diſcouered,
which is as followeth.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">When and how the ſhips ſet ſaile.</note>In
the yeare of our Lord 1595. vpon the 10. day of the month of March, there
departed from <hi>Amſterdam</hi> three ſhips and a Pinnace to ſayle into
the Eaſt <hi>Indies,</hi> ſet forth by diuers rich Marchantes: The firſt
called <hi>Mauritius,</hi> of the burthen of 400. tunnes, hauing in her ſixe
demie canon, fourteene Culuerins, and other pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, &amp; 4. peeces to ſhoot
ſtones, &amp; 84. men: the May<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Iohn Moleuate,</hi> the Factor
<hi>Cornelius Houtman:</hi> The ſecond named <hi>Hollandia,</hi> of the
burthen of 400. tunnes, hauing 85. men, ſeuen braſſe peeces, twelue
peeces for ſtones, and 13. iron peeces, the Mayſter <hi>Iohn Dignums,</hi>
the Factor <hi>Gerrit van Buiningen,</hi> the thirde called
<hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterdam,</hi> of the burthen of 200. tuns, wherein were 59. men,
ſixe braſſe peeces, ten iron peeces, and ſixe peeces for ſtones, the
Mayſter <hi>Iohn Iacobſon Schellinger,</hi> the Factor <hi>Reginer van
hel:</hi> The fourth being a Pinnace cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the <hi>Doue,</hi> of the burthen
of 50. tunnes, with twenty men, the Mayſter <hi>Simon Lambertſon:</hi>
Which 4. ſhips vpon the 21. of the ſame moneth came vnto the Taſſel,
where they ſtayed for the ſpace of 12. daies to take in <pb facs="tcp:9867:7"/> their
lading, and the ſeconde of Aprill following, they ſet ſaile with a North
eaſt winde &amp; following on their courſe the fourth of the ſame moneth
they paſſed the heades; The ſixt they ſaw <hi>Heyſſant,</hi> the
10. of April they paſſed by the Barles of <hi>Disbon:</hi> With an Eaſt
and North Eaſt wind, the 17. of Aprill they diſcouered two of the Iſlands
of <hi>Canaries:</hi> The 19. <hi>Palm,</hi> and <hi>Pic, Los Romeros,</hi> and
<hi>Fero:</hi> The 25. of Aprill they ſaw <hi>Bona viſita,</hi> the 16.
they ankered vnder <hi>Iſole de May:</hi> The 27. they ſet ſayle againe
and held their courſe South Southeaſt. The 4. of May, we eſpied two of
the King of <hi>Spaines</hi> ſhips, that came from <hi>Lisbone,</hi> and went
for the Eaſt <hi>Indies,</hi> about 1000. or 1200. tunnes each ſhip, with
whom we ſpake, and told them that we were bound for the ſtraights of
<hi>Magellanes,</hi> but being better of ſayle then they, wee got preſently
out of their ſight. The 12. of May being vnder fiue degrees on this ſide
the Equinoctiall line, we eſpyed fiue ſhips laden with Sugar, comming from
the Iſland of <hi>S. Thomas,</hi> and ſayled for <hi>Lisbone,</hi> to whome
we gaue certaine letters, which were ſafely deliuered in <hi>Holland.</hi>
Departing from them and keeping on our courſe, vpon the fourth of Iune we
paſſed the Equinoc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial line, where the extreame heat of the ayre ſpoyled
all our victuailes: 
<note place="margin">Their vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuailes ſtunke and
ſpoyled.</note>Our fleſh and fiſhe ſtunke, our Bisket molded, our Beere
ſowred, our water ſtunke, and our Butter became as thinne as Oyle, whereby
diuers of our men fell ſicke, and many of them dyed; but after that we
learned what meat and drinke we ſhould carrie with vs that would keepe good. 
<note place="margin">They paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the ſandes of
<hi>Braſilia.</hi>
               </note>The 28. of Iune wee paſſed the ſandes of
<hi>Braſill,</hi> by the Portingalles called <hi>Abrolhos,</hi> which are
certaine places which men muſt looke warely vnto, otherwiſe they are very
dangerous.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>map of Africa</figDesc>
               <head>AFRICA.</head>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:9867:8"/>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:9867:8"/>Theſe ſandes lie vnder 18.
degrees, and you muſt paſſe betweene the coaſt of <hi>Guine</hi> and
the ſandes afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, not going too neer eyther of them, otherwiſe
cloſe by the Coaſt there are great calmes, thunders, raines &amp;
lightnings, with great ſtormes, harde by the ſands men are in daunger to be
caſt away: and ſo ſayling on their courſe, firſt Eaſt South eaſt,
then Eaſt and Eaſt and by North. Vpon the ſeconde of Iuly wee paſſed
<hi>Tropicus Cancri,</hi> vnder 23. degrees, and ½. The <hi>13.</hi> of
the ſame Month, we eſpied many blacke birdes. 
<note place="margin">Tokens of the Cape <hi>de bona
Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance.</hi>
               </note>The <hi>19.</hi> great numbers of white birdes, and the
20. a bird as bigge as a Swan, whereof foure or fiue together is a good ſigne
of being neere the <hi>Cape de bona Sperance.</hi> Theſe birdes are alwaies
about the ſaid Cape, and are good ſignes of being before it.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">They en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into <hi>Agne
Sam<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bras</hi>
               </note>The ſecond of Auguſt we ſaw the land of the Cape
<hi>de bona Sperance,</hi> and the fourth of the ſame Month we entered into a
hauen called <hi>Agne Sambras,</hi> where wee ankered, and found good depth at
8. or 9. fadome wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, ſandy ground.</p>
            <p>The 5. day we went on ſhore to gather fruite, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with to
refreſh our ſicke men, that were thirty or 33. in one ſhippe. In this bay
lyeth a ſmal Iſlande, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in are many birdes called <hi>Pyncuius</hi> and
ſea Wolues that are taken with mens handes: we went into the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey and
ſpake with the inhabitantes, who brought di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers freſh victuailes aborde
our ſhippes, for a knife or ſmall peece of Iron, &amp;c. giuing vs an Oxe,
or a ſheepe &amp;c. The ſheepe in thoſe Countries haue great tayles, 
<pb facs="tcp:9867:9"/> and are fat and delicate. Their Oxen are indifferent good, hauing
lumps of fleſh vpon their backes, that are as fat as any of our good brisket
beefe: the inhabitantes are of ſmall ſtature, well ioynted and boned, they
goe naked, couering their members with Foxes and other beaſtes tayles: they
ſeeme cruell, yet with vs they vſed all kind of friendſhip, but are very
beaſtly and ſtinking, in ſuch ſort, that you may ſmell them in the
wind at the leaſt a fadome from you: They are apparrelled with beaſtes
skinnes made faſt about their neckes: ſome of them, being of the better
ſort, had their mantles cut &amp; rayſed checkerwiſe, which is a great
ornament with them: They eate raw fleſh, as it is new killed, and the
entrailes of beaſtes without waſhing or making cleane, gnawing it like
dogs, vnder their feet they tye peeces of beaſtes skinnes, in ſteed of
ſhooes, that they may trauel in the hard wayes: We could not ſee their
habitations, for wee ſaw no houſes they had, neither could wee
vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtande them, for they ſpeake very ſtrangely, much like the children
in our Countrey with their pipes, and clocking like Turkey Cockes: At the
firſt wee ſaw a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout thirtie of them, with weapons like pikes, with broade
heades of Iron, about their armes they ware ringes of <hi>Elpen</hi> bones:
There wee coulde finde ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Oringes nor Lemons, which we purpoſely
ſought for.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>map of St Lawrence [i.e. Madagascar]</figDesc>
               <head>I.S. Laurentij.</head>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:9867:10"/>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:9867:10"/>
               <note place="margin">With what wind
they ſailed to S. Laurence.</note>The <hi>11.</hi> of Auguſt we hoyſed
anker, ſayling towards the Iſland of <hi>S. Laurence,</hi> and the 22. of
the ſame Month we had a contrary wind that blew North eaſt: The 25. a
Weſt winde, and ſo held our courſe Eaſt North eaſt: The 28. there
blew a ſouth eaſt wind, &amp; the 30. a ſouth weſt winde, and our
courſe lay North North eaſt to ſayle to the Iſle of <hi>S.
Laurence.</hi> The firſt of September wee diſcouered the point of the
Iſlande of <hi>S. Laurence.</hi> vnder <hi>16.</hi> degrees, and the third
day we ſaw the Iſland being very deſirous to go on land, for that many of
our men were ſicke, whereby wee coulde hardly rule our ſhippes, or bring
them farther without healing, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhing of our men. 
<note place="margin">They had great ſtore of fiſh for 2 or 3.
kniues</note>The 9. of September <hi>Iohn Schel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linger</hi> ſent out his
boate to rowe to lande, where they founde three Fiſhermen, of whome for two
or three kniues they had great ſtore of fiſhes. The <hi>13.</hi> we entred
into a ſmall Bay, but becauſe wee founde no good anker ground, as alſo
being very foule we ſayled out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine. The 14. we ſayled vnder a ſmall
Iſland about a mile or 2. great, by the Hollanders called their Church yarde,
or the dead Iſland, becauſe many ſaylers dying in that place, were buried
in the <hi>African</hi> earth, and the 29. of the ſame Month died <hi>Iohn
Dignumſz</hi> Mayſter of the <hi>Lyon</hi> of <hi>Holland,</hi> and was
buried the next day after.</p>
            <p>There <hi>Iohn Peters</hi> of <hi>Delft</hi> Sayler of the
<hi>Hollandia,</hi> &amp; <hi>Koelken van Maidenblick</hi> of the
<hi>Amſterdam</hi> were ſet on ſhore vpon the Iſland of <hi>S.
Laurence,</hi> where they were left, becauſe they had committed certaine
notorious crimes.</p>
            <p>Meane time the Pinnace was ſent out to looke for freſh water,
which hauing found, the boat returned to bring vs newes, and therewith the
fleete ſayled thither, <pb facs="tcp:9867:11"/> and the 10. of October the ſhippes
ankered before the Riuer, and went on ſhore, where we found good proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
of all neceſſaries, the inhabitantes being very wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling thereunto,
bringing vs of al things that we needed, where for a Pewter Spoone wee had an
Oxe, or three ſheepe. 
<note place="margin">How the wilde men, aſſailed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and forced
them to inſconce the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues.</note>The <hi>11.</hi> of October we went on
ſhore with a boatfull of ſicke men, and the next day we were aſſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
by a company of wild men, againſt whom our wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons little preuayled, for
they hurt one of our men, and tooke all that we had from vs, whereby vpon the
thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth of the ſame Month, wee were forced to inſconſe ourſelues
with peeces of wood, and braunches of trees, making Cabins within our Sconſe,
for that the <hi>15.</hi> of October they came againe, but then we tooke one,
and ſlew another of them. The <hi>19.</hi> of Nouember our Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lot <hi>Claes
Ianſon</hi> was intrapped and murthered by the wild people, although we
vſed all the means we could to helpe him, but they feared no weapons, about
ten or twelue dayes after we tooke one of them that paide for his death. The
firſt of December our men hauing for the moſt part recouered their
healthes, were all car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed aborde the ſhips: 
<note place="margin">The maner &amp; cuſtome of the wild
people.</note>in that parte of <hi>Madagaſcar</hi> the people are of good
condition, and goe naked, onely with a Cotton cloth before their priuie
members, and ſome from their breaſts downward: Their ornaments are Copper
ringes about their armes, but Tin rings are more eſteemed with them, and
therefore Tinne with them is good Marchandiſe. Their Oxen haue great lumpes
of fat vpon their backes: Their ſheepes tayles way at the leaſt twelue
pound, being of an elle long, &amp; two and twentie inches thick. They gaue vs
ſix of thoſe ſheepe for a tinne Spoone: They dwel in cottages and 
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:9867:11"/> liue very poorely: they feare the noyſe of a peece, for
with one Caliuer you ſhall make an hundred of them runne away: Wee coulde not
perceyue any religion they had, but after wee were informed that they helde the
law of <hi>Mahomet,</hi> for the two boyes that wee tooke from of the land,
ſhewed vs their circumciſion: There we found no fruit of
<hi>Tambaxiumes,</hi> but great numbers of <hi>Parrats, Medicats,</hi> and
<hi>Turtle Doues,</hi> whereof we kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and eat many. The ſecond of
December we bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned our Sconſe, and fourteene of our men going fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther into
the Iſlande, brought certaine of the countrey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men priſoners, and being
abord our ſhips taught them what they ſhoulde doe. The thirteenth of
December wee hoyſed anker, minding to holde on our courſe for the Iſlands
of <hi>Iaua,</hi> &amp; for that by reaſon of the pleaſant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the
ayre we had in a manner all recouered our healthes, we ſet our courſe
Eaſt and by North, and Eaſt Northeaſt. The nineteenth of the ſame Month
wee were ſeperated by foule weather, &amp; the 22. with great ioy we met
againe. The tenth of Ianuarie <hi>Vechter Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemſon</hi> dyed, being a verie
honeſt man, and Pilot in <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenaers</hi> ſhippe, for whome we were much
grieued, and the ſame day we determined to put back againe for the Iſlande
of <hi>S. Laurence,</hi> for as then wee began againe to haue a great
ſcouring among our men, and many of them fell ſicke: 
<note place="margin">The wilde men brought things a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borde to comfort
them.</note>But preſently therevpon we eſpied the Iſlande of <hi>Saint
Mary,</hi> and the next day being arriued there, ſome of the inhabitants came
abord out ſhippes with a basket of Ryce, Sugar canes, Citrons, Lemons, &amp;
Hens, whereof we were very glad, as being phiſicke for vs.</p>
            <p>The 13. 14. 15. 16. and 17. dayes we were on land, <pb facs="tcp:9867:12"/>
where we bought Ryce, Hens, Sugar-canes, Citrons, and Lemons in great
aboundance, and other kinde of fruites to vs vnknowne, alſo good fiſh, and
greene Gin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger: There we tooke a Fiſh, which thirteen men could hardly pull
into our ſhippe, and becauſe the Iſland was little, and we had many men,
wee entred into the Bay of the firme land with our Pinnace, where for a
ſtring of Beades of ſmall value we had a tunne of Ryce: 
<note place="margin">The diſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of one of their
kings.</note>The King came abord our Pinnace to ſee it, &amp; was as blacke
as a Deuill, with two hornes made faſt vpon his heade, and all his body naked
like the reſt of the countrey peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</p>
            <p>This Iſland lyeth about a ſmall mile from
<hi>Madagaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>car,</hi> about 19. degrees Southward from the Equinocti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all line
(<hi>Madagaſcar</hi> or <hi>S. Laurence</hi> is an Iſlande belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to
the Countrey of <hi>Africa,</hi> and lyeth Southwarde vnder 26. degrees, ending
Northwarde vnder 11. de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees by the inhabitants it is called
<hi>Madagaſcar,</hi> &amp; by the <hi>Portingalles</hi> the Iſlande of
<hi>S. Laurence,</hi> becauſe it was diſcouered on <hi>S. Laurence</hi>
day: The riches of this Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land is great, it aboundeth in Ryce, Honnie, Waxe,
Cotton, Lemons, Cloues &amp;c. The inhabitantes are blacke and go naked, but
the haire vpon their heades is not ſo much curled as thoſe of the
<hi>Moſambique,</hi> &amp; they are not ful ſo blacke).</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The wilde people came on borde their ships and
ſeemed very friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>y.</note>The <hi>23.</hi> of Ianuary we ankered before a
Riuer where likewiſe we had all kind of neceſſaries, and after that we
went to lie vnder a ſmall Iſlande within the ſame Bay.</p>
            <p>The 25. of Ianuarie there came ſome of the wild peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple aborde our
ſhips, making ſignes to haue vs go on land, which we did, and there we had
good Ryce &amp; o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther fruits in great abundance: on the left ſide of the
en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try <pb n="8" facs="tcp:9867:12"/> of the Riuer lyeth one of their Townes, and on the
right hand two townes, where we had moſt of our tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fique. The <hi>26.</hi>
of Ianuarie wee had interpreters, whom we made to drink wine, wherewith they
were as drunk as beaſtes.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <head>The manner &amp; condition of the people inhabiting in the great
Bay of Antogil, on this ſide the Equinoctiall line vnder 16. degrees, on the
South ſide of the Iſland Madagaſcar.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is a very great Bay, about ten mile broade, behind it lyeth a
high Iſland, and three ſmall Iſlands: there is good harbour againſt all
windes. The Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land is inhabited, and therein grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth all kindes of fruites,
it hath a great fall of water that commeth down out of the hilles, where we
laded all our water, and halfe a mile from thence within the land, there
runneth a great Riuer, wherein likewiſe there is much water to be had, when
you enter into the Riuer about a quarter of a mile inward on the left hand,
ther is a ſmal towne or village, not cloſed nor fortified, in it there is
about 200. houſes, &amp; on the right hand where the Riuer diuideth it
ſelfe, there is two other ſuch Townes: They were all com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed with
palles, and the houſes were placed about two foote aboue the ground, vpon
foure or fiue palles or ſtakes of wood, and all the vpper partes of reede and
ſtrawe. 
<note place="margin">Why their houſes ſtand ſo high aboue the
earth.</note>The cauſe why their houſes are made ſo high from the ground,
is to auoide the danger of venemous beaſtes that are there in great
aboundance, as Serpents, <pb facs="tcp:9867:13"/> Snakes, Camelions, and other kindes of
beaſtes. 
<note place="margin">The maner of the wilde men in that
countrey.</note>The people are very blacke, but their hayre and beardes are not
ſo much curled as the right Mores, nor their noſes nor lippes ſo great
nor flat. They are ſubtill and ſtrong people, much addicted to drinking,
for they will bee as drunke as Swine, with a kind of drinke made of Honie &amp;
Ryce. They go naked, onely that about their midles they weare a cloth made of
the barke of a tree, drawne in ſmall threedes: they make and vſe very fine
Mats to ſitte vppon: They haue no great ſtore of weapons, for that halfe of
them are vnprouided, and that they vſe is a ſpeare of nine or ten foote
long, with a great wooden Target: They are very fearefull of our Caliuers, for
5. or ſixe men with Caliuers will cauſe great numbers of them to flie away:
We taught them what our Peeces ment, for wee perceyued that they knew them not,
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they had proued them: at the firſt they thought they coulde carry no
further then their owne lengthes, for they knew not what they were: Their
Kinges or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>namentes were ten or twelue Copper Rings about his armes: if we had
had ſuch Ringes with vs, wee might haue ſold them at what prices wee
woulde. They like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe vſe beades of Glaſſe, which they weare about
their armes and neckes, by them eſteemed for great orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: for a boxe of
beades of ſmall value, we had an Oxe, or three or foure Sheepe, rounde about
this Bay are townes and villages, where you may haue of all things to refreſh
your ſelues, Lemons and Citrons are there greater and better then in
<hi>Portingall:</hi> Likewiſe Oringes, Ryce, Hennes, Goats, Honie, and many
other ſortes of fruites, and to conclude it is the beſt Bay in all the
world to refreſh ſhips. Being on land we were wel <pb n="9" facs="tcp:9867:13"/>
entertayned, and muſt of force drink with them of their drinke made of Hony
and Ryce: There we trafiqued with them, and had ſufficient of euery thing,
but euery night we went aborde our ſhippes.</p>
            <p>The third of February we had ſo great a ſtorme, that moſt of
our ankers were loſt, and we ran vpon the land in great daunger to caſt our
ſhips away, but God holpe vs, for the ſtorme ceaſed, and then we went to
hoyſe vp our loſt ankers, and ſo againe went to anker vnder the Iſland,
glad that we had ſo well eſcaped that daunger. The fift of February we went
to ſeeke for our boats, but the wild men had ſmitten them in peeces, &amp;
taken out the nailes, thinking likewiſe that our ſhippes woulde haue beene
caſt away vpon the ſhore, which they ſtill expected: and when we came
thither, they ſtood vpon the ſhore with their weapons in hand and threw
ſtones at vs, and we perceyuing them in that minde, made to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes our
ſhippes, for we deſired not to reuenge our ſelues, nor once to fight with
them without commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from our Generall, whom we certified thereof. The
eyght of February we rowed into the Riuer to buy cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, and other things, but
they were become our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, threatning and caſting ſtones at vs,
wherevpon we put out two ſhalops to run a ſhore cloſe to the land, and
made our Caliuers and other weapons ready.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>map of Sumatra</figDesc>
               <head>SVMATRA INSVLA</head>
            </figure>
            <p>The 12. of Februarie wee hoiſed anker, and ſet ſayle out of
the great Bay of <hi>Antongil,</hi> being well prouided of all neceſſaries,
we put out with a North wind, the Bay ſtretching Northeaſt and Southweſt:
The 2. of March we had a Weſt winde, our courſe being Eaſt and Eaſt
&amp; by North towards <hi>Iaua.</hi> In March and Aprill about the Iſlande
of <hi>Brandawe,</hi> we found that our Compaſſes helde two Strikes to
farre Northwarde, and we coulde not perceiue the ſands that are ſet downe
in the <hi>Portin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>galles</hi> ſea Cards, but we ſaw many turnings of
ſtreames, and we were much troubled with calmes, but with the new Moone we
had winde enough out of the Weſt &amp; North weſt. The 27. of May we found
the water abord our ſhippes to bee much leſſened, and therefore euery
mans portion was but halfe as much as he was wont to haue; ſo that each man
was allowed but foure draughts euery day, which was but a ſmall quantitie.
Whereby through the extreame heat we endured great thirſt, ſo that at that
time a draught of water abord our ſhip was worth a Riall of 8. The firſt of
Iuly we ſaw the Iſlande of <hi>Emgano,</hi> whereat we much reioyced,
becauſe of the great thirſt wee endured in our ſhippe, and when wee made
neerer to it, we perceyued it to be an Iſlande ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing before the ſtraightes
of <hi>Sonda,</hi> vnder 9. degrees on the ſouth ſide of the line. The
ſixt of Iuly we put ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what nearer to the land, and there we ſaw ſixe
or ſeuen canes lying vnder the ſhore, but farre off, and durſt not 
<pb facs="tcp:9867:15"/> make toward vs: in the end we manned out a ſhalop &amp; rowed
to land, but they made from vs, &amp; when our men were hard by the ſhore,
there we ſaw about 40. or 50. of them ſtanding vpon the ſhore with their
bowes; wherewith our men durſt not land, for they ſeemed to be a cruell
kind of people, and altogether wild, for they went all naked, not hauing any
thing before their priuy members. They were of a reddiſh colour, but when our
men ſaw no aduantage they turned again vnto their ſhippes.</p>
            <p>The ſeuenth of Iuly we ſaw the point of the land of
<hi>Sumatra,</hi> which is a verie high land deſcending downe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde with a
long end.</p>
            <p>The 11. of the ſame Month we were cloſe vnder the land, where
there lay an Iſland, and there we ankered.</p>
            <p>The 12. of Iuly in the morning we ſaw certaine ſhips, whereof
one came vnto vs, wee rowed vnto it with a ſhalop, and ſpake with it, but
we could not vnderſtand them, but they ſhewed vs where we ſhould haue
water, which made vs glad, that wee might once againe haue our bellies full of
water: it being almoſt foure Monthes that wee had not ſeene any land, nor
taken in any freſh victuailes. We ſent our Pinace to the firme land of
<hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matra,</hi> there to ſeeke for ſome reliefe: for that where we lay
there dwelt not any man. 
<note place="margin">The maner of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernor of <hi>Sumatras</hi>
comming on bord.</note>The 13. of Iuly the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain or principall ruler of
<hi>Sumatra</hi> came abord our ſhips to ſee them, which was done with
great ſolemnitie, hee being apparelled after the Turkiſh manner, with a
wreath about his heade, and a fearefull countenance, ſmall eyes, great eye
browes, and little beard, for a man might tell all the haires vpon his chinne:
he brought vs a preſent of Betele, which are leaues which they conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually 
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:9867:15"/> chaw, and eat it with chalke.</p>
            <p>This Iſland of <hi>Sumatra</hi> or <hi>Taprobana</hi> (as it is
ſaide) is the greateſt of all the Orientall Iſlandes, it is diuided from
the firme land of <hi>Malacca</hi> by a ſtraight and dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous ſea, by
reaſon of many Iſlandes and cliffes that are within it: Out of this
Iſland as ſome men are of opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>Salomon</hi> had his Gold wherewith
he beautified the Temple, and his owne pallace, and then in the Bible it
ſhould be named <hi>Orphir,</hi> for certainly <hi>Sumatra</hi> is rich of
mynes of Golde, Siluer and Mettall, and the inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants therof are very expert
in melting of braſſe peeces: Therein is a fountaine of pure Balſame, the
<hi>Portingalles</hi> haue no fortreſſe therein, yet they traffique in
certaine hauens, ſpecially in <hi>Pedir</hi> and <hi>Campar:</hi> There is
alſo in this Iſland a place called <hi>Manancabo,</hi> where they make
poinyardes and daggers, by them calde cryſes, which are much eſteemed in
thoſe Countries, and thoſe of <hi>Malacca</hi> and <hi>Iaua,</hi> hold them
for their beſt weapons, and with them are very bold.</p>
            <p>The ſame day our Pinnace returned againe vnto vs, bringing vs good
newes, that wee were welcome vnto the Countrey people, and brought vs certaine
Indian Nuttes, or Cocus, Melons, Cocombers, Onions, Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke, and a ſample
of Peper and other ſpices, which li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked vs well.</p>
            <p>The fourteenth of Iune we laded in ſome freſh wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>map of Java</figDesc>
               <head>IAVA MAIOR</head>
            </figure>
            <p>The 15. of Iune there rowed a ſcute called a Prawen harde vnder
the lande by vs, wee called him, but not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his will, and ſhewed him
ſiluer, and other wares that liked him well, he bad vs make towards the
ſtrand, and told vs of <hi>Bantam,</hi> ſaying that there we ſhould haue
al kinds of Marchandiſe. Then we made ſigns vnto him taht if he wold bring
vs to <hi>Bantam,</hi> we wold pay him for his labor, he asked vs 5. rialles of
8. and a red cap, which we graunted vnto, and ſo one of the men in the
ſcute came on bord the <hi>Mauritius,</hi> and was our Pilot to
<hi>Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam,</hi> where we paſſed by many Iſlandes.</p>
            <p>The nineteenth of Iuly as wee ſailed by a towne, many
<hi>Portingalles</hi> borded vs, and brought vs certaine Cocus and Hens to
ſell, which wee bought for other wares.</p>
            <p>The <hi>22.</hi> of the ſame Month wee came before the towne of
<hi>Bantam,</hi> within three miles of it, and there an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kered vnder an
Iſland. The ſame day about euening a ſcute of <hi>Portingals</hi> borded
vs that were ſent by the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernour to ſee what ſhips we were, &amp; when
we ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them that wee came thither to traficke with them, 
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:9867:17"/> they told vs, that there was the right Pepper country,
&amp; that there we might haue our lading, that new Pep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per was readie to be
gathered, and would be ripe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in two Monthes after, which pleaſed vs well,
for wee had already beene fifteene Monthes and twelue daies vppon our voyage,
hauing endured great daungers, miſeries and thirſt, many of our men by
ſickneſſe being dead.</p>
            <p>The 23. of Iune wee hoyſed our ankers, and went cloſe to the
towne of <hi>Bantam,</hi> and ankered harde by 4. ſmall Iſlands, that lie
right North from the Towne: the ſame day the <hi>Sabandar</hi> (who is there
one of the greateſt officers next the King) came abord our ſhippes, asking
vs what we would haue, we ſaid we were come to buy Pepper and other ſpyces,
and that wee had readie mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, and certaine wares, whereof we ſhewed him
ſome parte, which hee liked well, ſaying that there wee might haue lading
enough, ſhewing vs great counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance.</p>
            <p>The ſame day likewiſe there came a great number of ſcutes vnto
our ſhips, bringing all kinds of victuailes to ſel, as Hennes, Egges,
Cocus, Bonanas, ſugar canes, Cakes of Ryce baked, and many other thinges. The
24. of Iune there came many men aborde our ſhips, bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing diuers wares to
ſell, ſhewing vs great friendſhippe, and as it ſeemed were very glad of
our arriuall there, tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling vs that there we might haue Pepper enough, and new
Pepper within two Months after, and that Pepper was then as good cheap as it
had beene any time with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ten yeares before, that wee might buy 5. or 6.
ſackes for one Catti, (being about 20. Guilderns) which was ordinarily ſold
but one ſacke for that price: euery ſacke <pb facs="tcp:9867:18"/> wayeth 54. pounde
<hi>Hollandes</hi> waight, ſo that a pounde would be worth about a braſſe
penie <hi>Hollands</hi> money. The ſame day about noone the <hi>Sabandar</hi>
borded vs once againe, willing <hi>Cornelis Houtman</hi> to go on land to
ſpeake with the Gouernour, for as then there was no King, for about a Month
before our arriuall there, the King was gone with a great armie before the
towne of <hi>Palimbam,</hi> which hee thought to take, and had almoſt gotten
it, but there he was ſtriken with a great Peece by a Renigado of the
<hi>Portingalles,</hi> and ſo was ſlaine. His death was much lamented by
the ſtraungers that dwelt at <hi>Bantam,</hi> for he was a good king, being
about 25. years of age: he left behind him foure wiues, whereof the el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt
was not aboue 15. yeares of age, and a yong ſonne of three Monthes olde, that
was to ſucceed him in his Kingdome, and they had choſen a Protector or
Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernor to rule in his minoritie, whom they call <hi>Kipate,</hi> and when
the <hi>Kipate</hi> by the <hi>Sabandar</hi> ſent to our Sarge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant Maior to
come vnto him into the towne, he made him anſwer that he had no ſuch
commiſſion, but he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired the Gouernor firſt to come abord his
ſhip, and then he would go on ſhore, he like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe deſired vs to go
neerer to the towne with our ſhippes.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:9867:18"/>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <pb facs="tcp:9867:19"/>
            <p> 
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of Bantam, Java</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:9867:19"/>
               <hi>THe Towne of</hi> Bantam <hi>in the Iſland
of</hi> Iaua, <hi>as our foure ſhippes lay before it</hi> A. <hi>is the barre
of the Riuer that was ſhutte vp, by it all wares paſſed both in and out,
and the next houſe vnto it is the cuſtome houſe.</hi> B. <hi>the
Hollanders lodging where we receyued and ſold our wares,</hi> C. <hi>is the
walles of the towne of</hi> Bantam, <hi>al made with flankers, vpon them lay
great ſtore of braſſe peeces, which when they ſhot at vs, did not much
hurt vs, becauſe they knew not wel how to vſe them; &amp; the wal is not
aboue two foot thicke made of brickes, and at euery place where the peeces
lyeth, there are places made of maſtes and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wood, which they vſe for
defence against the enemies.</hi> D. <hi>are the Portingalles houſes,</hi> E.
<hi>the Pepper market,</hi> F. <hi>the Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landers market,</hi> G. <hi>the
pomegranat market,</hi> H. <hi>the apparell market,</hi> I. <hi>the porſeline
market,</hi> K. <hi>the great market, which is alſo the Burſe where many
nations do meet,</hi> L. <hi>the Fiſh mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket,</hi> M. <hi>the hogge
market,</hi> N. <hi>the Chinars houſes,</hi> O. <hi>their Church or
Moſtua,</hi> P. <hi>a skirmiſh betweene our Pinace and 24. of their boates
that came towardes vs like a halfe Moon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> all full of men, armed with bowes and ſpeares, with ſome
baſes, making to the Pinace that lay on grounde vnder an Iſlande, where it
wound off, 17. of them being on the larborde, and 7. on the ſtarre borde of
her, ſo neare that they thruſt their ſpears in at her portes, but thoſe
of the Pinace ſhewed themſelues like men ſhooting brauely againſt them,
both with great ſhot and Caliuers for they could hardly ſhoot in vaine, and
hauing hoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſaile, ſhe came to the ſhippes againe in diſpight of
all her e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, that were in great numbers, and had compaſſed her about
like ſconces.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <pb facs="tcp:9867:20"/>
            <p>And therevpon wee ſayled ſomewhat neerer to the Iſland that
lay next vnto the towne, within halfe a mile from it, &amp; there we ankered at
4. fadome clay grounde, the towne lying South from vs, where wee had a good
roade: 
<note place="margin">The Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor of Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam came abord their
ſhips.</note>The next morning the Gouernor ſent aborde, and the men that
came ſpake not onely good <hi>Portingal,</hi> but other languages: he let our
Sargeant Maior vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand that he would come aborde, and deſired that hee
woulde with a ſhalop meet him halfe the way, which was done about noone, and
the Gouernour came a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borde with a great company of men, where we ſhewed him
all our wares, which liked him well, deſiring vs to come on land, ſaying
that we ſhould be welcome, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſing vs much fauour, wherewith he returned
to the land with certaine rich preſents that we gaue him. The <hi>26. Barent
Heijn</hi> Factor of the ſhip called the <hi>Mauritius,</hi> died very
ſodainly.</p>
            <p>The 27. and 28. great numbers of people borded our ſhippes
bringing all ſortes of neceſſaries &amp; victuails to ſell.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour came aborde and ſecretly
con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſpired with the Portin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gals againſt them.</note>The 29. there came an
Emperour abord our ſhippe, whoſe father in time paſt had beene Emperour
of all <hi>Iaua,</hi> and commanded all the Kinges of <hi>Iaua,</hi> but this
man becauſe of his badde life was not much accounted of: he ſpake good
<hi>Portingall,</hi> for his mother was a <hi>Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingall</hi> woman borne in
<hi>Malacca:</hi> This Emperour had conſpired againſt vs with the
<hi>Portingalles,</hi> but as then we knew it not.</p>
            <p>The 30. of Iune <hi>Cornelis Houtman</hi> tooke a boate and went
into the towne, and there ſpake with the Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour about certaine affaires,
touching a contract to bee made with him.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:9867:20"/>
               <note place="margin">A contract to buy &amp;
ſell in the towne.</note>The firſt of Iuly <hi>Houtman</hi> went again into
the towne, and when he returned he brought with him a certaine contract made
&amp; ſigned by the Gouernor himſelf, who moſt willingly conſented
therevnto, &amp; ſaide vnto him, Go now and buy what you will, you haue free
liberty; which done, the ſaid <hi>Houtman</hi> with his men went to ſee the
towne, apparelled in the beſt manner they coulde, in veluet, Satin, and
ſilkes, with rapiers by their ſides: The Captaine had a thing borne ouer
his head to keep him from the Sun, with a Trumpet before him, which certaine
times he cauſed to bee ſounded: There the Emperour bad them to a banket
after the <hi>Indian</hi> man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner: From thence they went to the
<hi>Portingalles,</hi> that made much account of <hi>Houtman,</hi> and made him
a ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket, ſaying that they had ſeene him in <hi>Lisbone.</hi> The 2. of
Iuly many Marchants came abord, profering vs Pep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per verie good cheape, but
becauſe we were vnskilfull in the waight and other thinges wee tooke
reſpite to anſwere them.</p>
            <p>The 3. of Iuly the <hi>Sabander</hi> came abord, and he was our
great friend, for that after we found it ſo, hee tolde vs what waight the
ſackes of Pepper were, and what priſes they bare, counſelling vs to
buy.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour ment to fall vpon the ſhips to
rob them.</note>The 7. of Iuly the Gouernour ſent vs a man ſecret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by
night willing vs to looke vnto our ſelues, and not to truſt the Emperour,
with whom all the Marchantes conſpired, and went to inuade our ſhips, and
that hee ment to rob vs, as being very licentious and euill mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
            <p>The 8. of Iuly the Emperour ſent vnto our ſhips, &amp; offered
to make them a banket, bidding all the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, maiſters, Pilots,
Gentlemen, Officers, Trumpets, <pb facs="tcp:9867:21"/> and Gunners to come into the towne
to him, and there he woulde make merrie with them: This was done by the
<hi>Portingalles</hi> aduiſe, thereby to haue all the chiefe and principall
men out of our ſhips, but we perceiued their intent.</p>
            <p>The 11. of Iuly the Emperour perceyuing that his deuiſe would not
take place, hee went from <hi>Bantam</hi> to <hi>Iacatra.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 12. of Iuly wee had a houſe offered vs within the towne.</p>
            <p>The 13. of the ſame month <hi>Reyner van hel</hi> with eyght
Gentlemen went into the towne, taking certaine wares with him, of euery thing a
little, and laid it in the houſe appointed for the purpoſe: there to keep a
ware houſe and to ſel our marchandiſe, and preſently both Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men
and Marchants came thither to buy and to ſell vs Pepper.</p>
            <p>The 15. and 16. many Gentlemen, Marchants, Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nars, and Arabians
came to our warehouſe &amp; into our ſhips, offering vs Pepper, but our
Factor offered them too little a price.</p>
            <p>The 25. of Iuly the Gouernour came againe aborde our ſhippes, and
there looked vppon certaine of our wares, whereof hee bought ſome, and
counſelled vs to buy Pepper: 
<note place="margin">The hatred of the Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingalles a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note>About the ſame time the <hi>Portingalles</hi> made great ſute
vnto the Gouernour, promiſing him many guiftes to deny vs trafficke, and to
conſtraine vs to depart from thence, ſaying we were no marchantes, but that
we came to ſpie the countrie, for they ſaid that they had ſeene many
<hi>Fleminges</hi> in <hi>Lisbone,</hi> but none like vs. Among the
<hi>Portingalles</hi> there was one that was borne in <hi>Malacca,</hi> of the
<hi>Portingalles</hi> race, his name was <pb n="19" facs="tcp:9867:21"/> 
               <hi>Pedro
Truide,</hi> a man well ſeene in trauayling, and one that had beene in all
places of the world: He was our good friend, &amp; euery day came to talke with
our Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, ſaying, you do not well that you make no more haſte to take
in your lading, you ſhall haue no better cheape wares, &amp; withall ſhewed
vs many other things: wherevpon the <hi>Portingalles</hi> hated him, and not
long af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he was murthered in his bed.</p>
            <p>In Auguſt we did little, and tooke no great ſtore of lading in
ſeeking to haue Pepper better cheape, which the <hi>Portingalles</hi> liked
not well of, and ſaide vnto the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernour, that we deſired not to buy;
which the Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour began to hearken vnto, for they offered him great ſummes
of money that hee ſhoulde not permit vs traf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fique, ſo that in the end hee
commaunded that no man ſhoulde carrie any Ryce aborde our ſhippes, whereby
we were abaſhed, and thereupon we ſent vnto the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernour for our money
which hee ought for the wares hee had bought, which moued him. The 26. of Iuly
hee ſent one of our Gentlemen with ſome of his men and nine ſlaues abord
our ſhips.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <pb facs="tcp:9867:22"/>
            <head>The ſituation of the Towne of <hi>Bantam,</hi> the principall
towne of traffique in the Iſland of <hi>Iaua,</hi> their ſtrength &amp;
manner of building, with their traffique, what people come thither, what wares
are there moſt deſired, what nations bring them thither, or come to fetch
them, together with their religion, cuſtomes, &amp; manner of houſe
keeping.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Antam</hi> lyeth in the Iſlande of <hi>Iaua maior,</hi>
about 25. miles to ſea ward within the Iſle, betweene <hi>Suma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra</hi> and
<hi>Iaua:</hi> On both ſides of the Towne there runneth a Riuer, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout 3.
foot and a half deep, ſo tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> no
ſhippes can enter into them: The Towne is compaſſed about with a Riuer:
The towne is almoſt as great in compaſſe as the old towne of
<hi>Amſterdam:</hi> The wals are made with flankers: They haue great numbers
of Peeces therein, but they knowe not how to vſe them, for they feare them
much: all their Peeces are of braſſe, &amp; they haue many brazen baſes.
Their walles are not aboue two foote thicke made of brickes: euery flanker hath
di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers maſtes and peeces of wood, which they vſe when they are beſieged
by their enemies. The houſes are made of ſtraw and reedes, ſtanding vpon
4. woodden poſtes. The rich haue their chambers all hanged with ſilken
Curtins, or els with cotton linnen: Their houſes are moſt placed vnder
Cocus trees, whereof the towne is full: Without the walles are many houſes,
wherein ſtrangers for the moſt part haue their dwellinges. The 
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:9867:22"/> towne hath three great market places, wherein dayly there
is markets holden, where you may buy all kindes of wares, and where there
commeth a great number of people, very ſtrange to beholde: Within the towne
there is a great church or muske of wood, wherein they obſerue the law of
<hi>Mahomet:</hi> Gentlemen &amp; men of any qualitie haue their owne muskes in
their houſes. The towne is not built with ſtreetes, nor the houſes placed
in order, but very foule lying full of filthy wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, which men muſt
paſſe through, or leape ouer, for they haue no bridges: In the towne there
is great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſort of diuers Countries and nations, as of <hi>Malacca,
Ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gala, Malabar Guihereters</hi> of <hi>Pegu, Sani Malicas, Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da,
China,</hi> and of many Kingdomes that haue great traf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fique for Pepper, that
groweth rounde about <hi>Bantam,</hi> which in Auguſt and September is ripe,
there you haue Nutmegs, out of the Iſland of <hi>Banda,</hi> and Cloues from
<hi>Moluca,</hi> which the <hi>Portingalles</hi> doe moſt buy vp: Wee bought
Nutmegs there for a blank a pound: All victu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ailes and neceſſaries are
there in great aboundance to be had, as Hennes, Hartes, Fiſh, and Ryce, and
diuers kindes of fruites, as Auanas, Cocus, Bonanas, Manges, Doroyens, Iacca,
Pruna, Grapes, Oranges, Lemons, Pomegarnets, Cocombers, Melons, Onions,
Garlicke; but breade they haue none, but in ſteade of it they eate Ryce:
Beefe is there the deareſt victuaile, for an Oxe in that place is worth 7. 8.
or 9. Rialles of 8. The Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nars haue the greateſt and moſt trafficke in
that towne. They come thither in the Month of Ianuarie, with 8. or 9. great
ſhippes, bringing all ſorts of Porſeline, ſilks, Damaske, gold thread,
Iron pannes, and <hi>Iauas</hi> money called <hi>Caixas,</hi> whereof 12000.
make a Ryall of eyght: <pb facs="tcp:9867:23"/> They are hanged vpon ſtringes by two
hundred toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, for the which they both buy &amp; ſel al kinds of
mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandiſes, and there they lade Pepper which they car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie into
<hi>China:</hi> Without the towne they haue a great place wherein they commonly
vſe to ſell their wares, and there they dwell, and haue greater and better
hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes then any are within the towne, all made of reedes, onely that in
euery houſe they haue a ſquare place made of ſtone, wherein they put
their wares to keepe them from burning, as ſome riche men in the towne
likewiſe haue: The <hi>Chinars</hi> are very ſubtill and indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious
people, and will refuſe no labour nor paynes to yearne money, there they make
much Aqua vitae of Ryce and Cocus, and trafficke much therewith, which the
<hi>Iauars</hi> by night come to buy, and drinke it ſecretly, for by
<hi>Mahomets</hi> law it is forbidden them. The <hi>Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nars</hi> liue there
with free libertie: When they come to remaine there for a yeare or more as they
thinke good, they buy themſelues a wife or two, or more as they thinke good,
and liue together like man and wife, and when they meane to depart, they ſell
their wiues again, but if they haue children they take them with them, &amp;
ſo returne to <hi>China:</hi> They haue no ſpecial religion, but pray vnto
the Deuill, that he would not hurt them, for they know that the Deuill is
wicked, and that God is good, and hurteth no man, therefore they thinke it
needleſſe to pray to God. They acknowledge not the reſurrection of the
deade, but when a man dyeth they thinke he neuer riſeth again: In their
houſes they haue great painted Deuils, before the which they place wax
candles, and ſing vnto them, praying them not to hurt them, and the more
monſtrous that their ſhapes be, the <pb n="21" facs="tcp:9867:23"/> more they honour
them. Theſe people liue very hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and poorely within <hi>Bantam,</hi> for
there is not any work or labour how filthy ſoeuer it be, but they will do it
to get money, and when they haue gotten ſomething they returne again to
<hi>China.</hi> They are verie like Iewes in our countrey, for they neuer goe
without a paire of ballances, and all thinges is good wares with them, and are
ready to do any ſeruice. When we came firſt before <hi>Bantam,</hi> they
came euery day in great companies into our ſhippes, and there ſet out their
wares to ſel, as ſilkes, ſowing ſilkes, and porſelines, ſo that our
vpper deckes were full of pedlers, that wee could hardly walke vpon the
hatches.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <head>The manner, condition, cuſtome, going, ſtanding, apparell,
houſekeeping, wares, and behauiour of the Iauars in Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He <hi>Iauars</hi> and inhabitants of <hi>Bantam,</hi> are proude
and obſtinate, with a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſtately pace, they hold the law of
<hi>Mahomet,</hi> which they haue not had aboue <hi>35.</hi> yeares, for as yet
there are many heathens among them that ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer were made <hi>Mores:</hi> it is
a very ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and theeuiſh kind of people, not in any ſort to bee
truſted. Their apparell both of rich and poore is a cot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton cloth, and ſome
of ſilke about their middles, which they tie about them with a girdle, the
vpper parte and from the knees downewarde all naked: moſt of them goe
bareheaded, but the principalleſt of them haue a wreath or Turkiſh roule
about their heades, and ſome <pb facs="tcp:9867:24"/> little cappes: Their prieſtes
come out of <hi>Meca</hi> in <hi>Arabia,</hi> and are yellowe of colour: 
<note place="margin">What wea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pons they weare.</note>Their weapon is a
poinyard, which they call Criſis: it is made with hilts, &amp; the handle is
a Deuil cut out of wood or bone: the ſheathes are of wood: with them they are
very bolde, and it is accounted for a great ſhame with them if they haue not
ſuch a Dagger, both yong, old, rich &amp; poore, and yong children of fiue or
ſixe yeares olde, and when they go to the warres they haue targets, and
ſome long ſpeares, but moſt of them ſuch poinyardes: They vſe neyther
great ſhotte nor caliuers when they go againſt their enemies: for a ſmall
matter one King wil make warre againſt another When we came firſt before
<hi>Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam,</hi> we offered to make a contract with the Gouernor and the
counſell of the towne, that they ſhould deliuer vs a certaine quantitie of
Pepper, and wee woulde goe with our ſhippes before <hi>Palimbam,</hi> and
helpe them to reuenge the death of their Kings vppon their enemies, for (as
they ſaid) we might goe within a bowe ſhot of the towne with our ſhippes,
and the Towne is but of wood without walles, ſo that we would preſently
haue beaten it downe to the ground. They offered vs ſome of their principall
Gouernours to be left for pledges in our ſhippes, and their men woulde
ſayle in their fuſtes, ſuch as ſhoulde go on land, and we ſhould doe
nothing els but ſhoote out of our ſhippes, but our Captaines would not do
it, conſidering our ſmall number of men. 
<note place="margin">How many wiues they haue.</note>The
<hi>Iauers</hi> take as many wiues as they will, and are able to maintaine; but
the common people haue but one, &amp; ſome two marryed wiues, and ſome 10.
20. &amp; 30. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cubines: For a ſmall matter they will ſende their
mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried wiues home agayne vnto their fathers, when they <pb n="22" facs="tcp:9867:24"/>
haue layne fiue or ſixe dayes with them, ſaying they like them not, and
ſo their marriage is vndone, when they deſire it.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <head>The manner, cuſtome, houſholding, childbearing, ſporting
&amp; cleanlineſſe of the women in <hi>Bantam.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He women of the towne are well kept from ſuch as are
circumciſed, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the rich men haue many, and from other men or their
friendes, for their owne ſonnes may not come into the houſe where the women
are. They lie all naked and chaw Betelle, and haue a ſlauiſh wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man that
continually ſcratcheth their bodies, that is, ſuch as are married women,
but ſuch as are concubines are as waiting Gentlewomen to the married women,
when they goe out to giue them more maieſtie, and thoſe that haue the
greateſt number are of moſt eſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: The Concubines haue but fewe
children, for the married women poyſon their children, and theſe concubines
are bought and ſolde: by their apparell a man can hardly diſcerne the riche
from the poore, for they goe all with a Cotton cloth about their bodies vp to
their breaſtes, and bounde about their middles with an other cloth, bare
footed and their heads vncouered, their hayre bound right vpon the top of their
heads in a heape, but when they are in their pride, they weare crownes vpon
their heads, whereof ſome of them are of pure golde, &amp; ringes of golde,
&amp; ſome of ſiluer about their armes, euery one according to their
abilitie. They are very curious about their bodyes, for they waſhe 
<pb facs="tcp:9867:25"/> themſelues at the leaſt fiue or ſixe times euery day: they
neuer eaſe themſelues nor haue the company of their husbandes, but they
preſently leape into the water and waſh their bodies, and therefore the
water that runneth through <hi>Bantam</hi> is very vnholeſome; for euery one
wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth themſelues in it, as well pockie as other people, whereby wee
loſt ſome of our men that drunke of the water: The women are verie idle,
for they do nothing all the day but lie downe; the poore ſlaues muſt doe
all the drudgerie, and the men ſit all day vpon a mat, &amp; chaw
<hi>Betele,</hi> hauing ten or twentie women about them, and when they make
water, preſently one of the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men waſheth their member, and ſo they
ſit playing all the day with their women: Many of them haue ſlaues that
play vppon inſtrumentes much like our Shakebois, they haue likewiſe great
baſons whereon they ſtrike, &amp; therewith know how to make good
muſicke, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at the women daunce, not leaping much, but winding and drawing
their bodies, armes and ſhoulders, which they vſe all night long, ſo that
in the night time they make a great noyſe with baſons and other
inſtruments, and the man he ſitteth and looketh vpon them, euerie one of
the women ſtriuing to doe her beſt that ſhe may get her husbands fauour
and her ſecreat pleaſure. The Gentlemen, Citizens, and marchantes haue
their Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens, and fieldes without the towne, and ſlaues for the purpoſe
to labour in them, and bring their maiſters all kindes of fruit, Rice and
Hennes in the towne, 
<note place="margin">How Pep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in that countrey.</note>as
alſo the Pepper that groweth there, which runneth vp by an other tree, as
Hoppes with vs, and groweth in long bunches like Grapes, ſo that there is at
the leaſt 200. graines in one bunch: it is firſt greene, and after it
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commeth <pb n="23" facs="tcp:9867:25"/> blacke, and is there in great aboundance, ſo
that it is the right Pepper countrey; for when we came thither they ſaid vnto
vs, <hi>Aqui ai tanta Pimienta, como terra,</hi> that is, here is as much
Pepper as earth, and ſo we found it, and yet we departed from thence by our
own follies, without our lading of Pepper: Wee ſtaide for new Pepper, meane
time the <hi>Portingalles</hi> ſent their let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters into euery place ſeeking
to hinder our trade: At the firſt we might haue ſufficient, for there we
founde enough both to buy for money or to barter. We like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe had money and
wares ſufficient: we might eaſily haue had ſixe or eight hundred tunnes,
as we were ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertiſed by ſome of the countrey, that we ſhould
pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently buy, for that the <hi>Portingalles</hi> ſought all the means
they could to hinder vs, as after it appeared; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he that thinketh
to come ſoone enough, commeth oftentimes too late, and we vſed not our time
ſo well as it fell out.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">A letter ſent by our men in the town that were
kept priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners.</note>The 29. of Auguſt we had a letter ſent vs by night
from our men that were in the towne, that lay in a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner as priſoners, to
will vs to let our pledge go a ſhore, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe they feared they ſhoulde
hardly eſcape with their liues, and great danger might fall vpon them: this
pledge came aborde with the 9. ſlaues.</p>
            <p>The 30. of Auguſt we ſent the pledge and the reſt of our
<hi>Iauers</hi> to land, with promiſe that he would do the beſt he might to
get our men leaue to come aborde: a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout euening of the ſame day wee had
newes from our men by foure of our ſaylers that as then they were bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
vſed, ſaying they thought they ſhould come aborde when two ſhippes were
gone that ment to ſaile for <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacca,</hi> being laden with Nutmegs and
other things.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:9867:26"/>The firſt of of September, and the 2. 3. and 4. wee
ſent many letters to the Gouernour and hee to vs, and likewiſe to our men
that were in the towne, being nine in number, all our beſt marchants and
captains, hauing with them about 6. or 7000. Guildernes in marchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe, and
they againe to vs.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">They went nearer to the towne.</note>The 5. of
September when wee perceyued that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>layes were daungerous, wee went cloſe to
the towne with all our 4. ſhippes, and ſo neere that we had but two fadome
muddie grounde, and preſently with two of our boates for our ſecuritie wee
ſet vppon three <hi>Iauan</hi> ſhippes, whereof two were laden with fiſh
and Cocus, wherein wee founde a man of <hi>China,</hi> being of ſome account.
The third ſhip was laden with 20. tunnes of Cloues, 6. tunnes of Pepper, and
ſome Benioni, and <hi>Piementa da Rauo,</hi> wherein we founde fiue
<hi>Malabardes</hi> ſlaues to the <hi>Portingalles,</hi> whom wee likewiſe
tooke, &amp; they were very willing to goe with vs, thereby to bee eaſed of
the ſlauery wherevnto the <hi>Portingals</hi> put them, and perceyuing that
the <hi>Portingalles</hi> went often to and from another ſhippe that lay not
farre from vs, we took our Pinace and made towardes it, and being harde by it,
the <hi>Portingals</hi> left it &amp; ſet it on fire: This ſhip had the
richeſt wares in it as the <hi>Portingalles</hi> ſlaues tolde vs, for it
was laden with fiftie tunnes of Cloues, which were burnt in it.</p>
            <p>The ſixt and ſeuenth of September we hearde no newes, ſo that
wee went cloſe to the Towne agayne, ſhooting with our great Peeces into it,
ſlaying diuers of the people (as after we were informed:) They likewiſe
ſhot with their Peeces agaynſt vs, which the <hi>Portingalles</hi> did, for
that the <hi>Iauars</hi> haue little or no skill at all there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, 
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:9867:26"/> and are very fearefull of them, and although they had many
peeces in the towne, yet they did vs no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hurt then onely ſhot one of
<hi>Molenares</hi> halfe maſts in peeces.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">A skirmiſh betweene the Pinace &amp; 24.
boats</note>The ſeuenth of September wee had a skirmiſh, which was in this
manner, we perceyuing a <hi>Iauan</hi> ſhip vnder ſayle, ſent our Pinace
with ſixe and twentie men in her to fetch it in, which the <hi>Iauan</hi>
ſhippe perceyuing fledde behinde an Iſlande, where our Pinace followed him
ſo faſt that ſhee fell a grounde, which the townes men perceyuing, made
them readie with foure and twentie boates full of men, all armed after their
man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and ſet forwarde in good order, being diuided in two companies,
ſeuen on ſtarre bord, &amp; 17. on lardde bord of the Pinace, in order like
a halfe Moone, threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning vs with their ſpeares, they thought by reaſon of
their great number of men, that they had already taken it, but it fell out
otherwiſe, for they in the Pinace per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyuing them comming, ſhotte among
them, and they were ſo near vnto her that we could not ſhoot at them: and
when they were harde by the Pinace, ſhee gotte a flote, as they thought to
take her, hauing caſt out an anker in good time, and thereby wounde
them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues off the grounde, but for haſte they were for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to cutte their
Cable, becauſe they had not time enough to winde it vppe, and with all they
ſhotte one of their boates vnder water. The Pinace draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her boate after
her, the <hi>Iauans</hi> preſently leapt into it, and cutte a ſunder the
roape that helde it, which they immediately ſtole from vs, thruſting vvith
their Speares in at the loope holes. Seuen of their Boates being round about vs
were ſo ſharpely <pb facs="tcp:9867:27"/> paid with the iron peeces, ſtone peeces,
and Caliuers, that the 17, others durſt not come ſo neere vs: I thinke
there were at the leaſt 100. of them that neuer carryed newes how they ſped
in that skirmiſh, for euery boate had at the leaſt 60. men in it, and they
were ſo thicke in them, that they could not help themſelues, nor did any
thing els but ſhake their ſpeares, and they ſhot but one baſe: their
arrowes hurt vs not, and ſo the Pinace retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned againe vnto our ſhippes,
ſayling cloſe before the towne, and ſhooting into it with her ordinance:
They ſhot out of the towne, but it hit her not, becauſe they ſhot with
ſtone pellets, wherewith you cannot ſhoote ſo certainly as with iron
bullets.</p>
            <p>The 8. 9. and 10. of September we had letters from our men out of
<hi>Bantam,</hi> by the which they willed vs not to ſhoot any more, for that
the Gouernour threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to ſet them vpon ſtakes: <hi>Houtman</hi> wrote
they were in good hope that they ſhoulde bee put to raunſome, which wee
counſelled them to doe as well as they might.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents of the Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors letter.</note>The
11. of September we had a letter from <hi>Houtman,</hi> and one from the
Gouernour, wherein hee wrote that he would ſet our men at libertie, ſo we
would be quiet, but if we deſired warre, he woulde once againe come and
viſite vs in another ſort: wee aunſwered him that there he ſhould find
vs, that wordes were but wind, &amp; that he ſhould ſet our men at a
reaſonable ranſome, and thereof ſend vs an anſwere the next day.</p>
            <p>The 12. and 13. of September wee had no anſwere out of the towne,
and we had want of water, and could get none thereabouts but that which came
out of the towne, for that the Gouernour had taken order that we 
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:9867:27"/> ſhould get no water about the towne, ſo that we
hoiſed ankers to go ſeeke ſome.</p>
            <p>The 17. of September we came before 3. or 4. Iſlands which
<hi>Molenare</hi> and <hi>Shellenger</hi> ſayled betweene, and for that the
ſtreame ranne ſo ſtrong there, they were forced to goe ſo nigh the
ſhore, that they might al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt leape on lande, whereby they eſcaped great
dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, but the other ſhippe and the Pinace ſayled about the Iſlands,
and ſo met with the other two, and caſting forth their ankers went on
ſhore, where wee ſpake with men that ſaide they would ſhew vs where wee
ſhoulde haue water, ſo we would giue them two Caliuers.</p>
            <p>The 18. 19. 20. 23. and 24. we ſtayed to lade water, for it was
hard to get, and we were forced to keep good watch, which done hoyſing ankers
againe, wee ſayled towardes <hi>Bantam,</hi> holding our courſe
Eaſtwarde.</p>
            <p>The 27. we ſayled Northeaſt towardes the lande of <hi>Iaua
maior.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 28. ſetting ſayle agayne, we kept Eaſt North<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſt along
by the coaſt of <hi>Iaua,</hi> &amp; about noone becauſe of the great
ſtreame that runneth in the ſtraight, wee were forced to anker, and the 30.
day wee ſet ſayle a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine.</p>
            <p>The firſt of October in the euening wee came to a great Iſlande,
being three miles from the towne, and there we ankered finding good clay
ground.</p>
            <p>The 2. of October wee had a letter from our men, how they were
ſeperated one from the other, and kept by the Gentlemen of the towne, and
their wares parted among them.</p>
            <p>The 3. 4. and 5. when wee were againe before the towne, we had other
letters, that by our comming they <pb facs="tcp:9867:28"/> were better vſed, and hoped
to bee ſet at a reaſonable ranſome, and that they promiſed that one of
our men ſhould come aborde, ſo he would returne againe into towne, that
ſhoulde by worde of mouth certifie vs what hope they were in, and the cauſe
thereof, that we might the better belieue it.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">How the Iaurs vſed our men being
pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners.</note>The 6. of October in the night one of our men came aborde,
and ſhewed vs what had paſt, when we ſhotte into the towne, how they were
ſeperated and kept cloſe priſoners, and cruelly threatned by the
<hi>Iauers,</hi> whereby they ſtill expected when they ſhould bee put to
death, and howe they ſought all the meanes they coulde to make them to deny
their faith, and become <hi>Mores,</hi> but they remayned conſtant, and
ſaide they woulde rather die, and that they had by force ſhauen three of
our men after the <hi>Moriſh</hi> manner, and how the <hi>Portingals</hi> had
ſought all the meanes they coulde to buy them for ſlaues, offering money
for them that they might ſende them to <hi>Malacca,</hi> how they were ſet
at libertie againe, &amp; might goe where they woulde within the towne, and
ſo they hoped all would be well, and that they ſhoulde bee ſet at
libertie for ſome ſmall ranſome, and that the Gouernour asked them 3000.
Rialles of 8. but they hoped to bring him to 2000. whereat we much
reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced.</p>
            <p>The 8. 9. and 10. of October we paſſed ouer to make ſome
agreement with them that we might be quiet.</p>
            <p>The 11. of October they agreede vppon a ranſome of 2000. Ryalles
of eyght, and were content, that what goodes ſoeuer we had taken from them,
wee ſhoulde keepe as our owne, and for our goodes that they had ſtolen, and
forcibly taken from our men within the <pb n="26" facs="tcp:9867:28"/> towne, 
<note place="margin">The maner of their ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome.</note>they would
keepe them, and ſo exchange one for the other, they likewiſe were content
to quit vs of all our debts, that we ought within the towne eyther to the
Gouernor or to any other man, and that from thence forwarde we ſhould be
free, and traffique in the towne, both to buy and ſell when it pleaſed vs,
&amp; with their good willes as we had done, and before we paide our money, the
towne was to ſende two men aborde our ſhips, which done, we were to pay the
halfe of our ranſome, and vpon the payment thereof, they ſhoulde ſet
halfe of our men at liberty, and that halfe of our men being come aborde, wee
were to pay the other halfe of our ranſome, which was 1000. Ryalles of eyght;
which being performed, their two men, and their other halfe of our men were on
both ſides to bee deliuered and ſette free, and without contradiction it
was perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med.</p>
            <p>The 12. and 13. this agreement being ended, diuers victuailers came
aborde our ſhippes to ſell vs Hennes, Egges, and all other kind of
victuailes.</p>
            <p>The 14. we gaue certaine preſentes in ſigne of good will, to
ſuch as had ſhewed vs fauour when we were in contention with them.</p>
            <p>The 15. 16. 17. and 18. ſome of our Factors went into the towne,
where they bought certaine Pepper, &amp; brought it abord our ſhips.</p>
            <p>The 19. they went again into the towne, &amp; bought a greater
quantitie at 5. ſackes for one Catti, minding in that ſorte euery day to
take in our lading, but it fell not out as wee deſired, for the
<hi>Portingalles</hi> that coulde not brooke our company, made ſuch means to
the Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, that he gaue commandement that we ſhould buy <pb facs="tcp:9867:29"/> no
more Pepper, before we had paide 1400. Rialles of 8. which he challenged of vs
becauſe we had caſt anker within his ſtreame, whereupon our Marchantes
went and agreed with him, which done wee thinking to buy Pepper as we did
before, 
<note place="margin">Why the Gouernor forbad vs trafficke.</note>the
Gouernour againe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to the contrarie, whereby we perceyued their
deceipt, in that he wold not hold his word. The coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try men would gladly haue
ſolde their Pepper, as alſo the <hi>Chinars, Arabians, Mahometitians,</hi>
and ſecretly ſome <hi>Portingalles,</hi> but when we ſaw wee could not
get it out but with great daunger, wee thought it not conuenient to buy: and
when we ſpake vnto the Gouernour, tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the holding of his worde, he made
vs anſwere, that he had no bones in his tongue, and that therefore he could
ſpeake that which he ment not to doe: and to ſay the truth moſt part of
the <hi>Iauars</hi> are a kind of deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full people, for whatſoeuer they
ſay and preſently per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme, that ſhall you be ſure of and no more.</p>
            <p>The 25. of October there came an Ambaſſador into
<hi>Bantam,</hi> ſent from <hi>Malacca</hi> to the Gouernor with a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
of 10000. Rials of 8. deſiring him to forbid vs both his towne and ſtreame,
that wee might not traffique there. Whereof wee were aduertiſed by the
<hi>Sabandar</hi> and other of our friendes counſelling our men to get them
out of the towne, and not to returne again, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe they would be in
daunger to be ſtayed againe, and we hauing ſent a man into the towne to
ſaue him from being holden priſoner, our hoſt where we lay being on
ſhore was forced to bring him out couered with cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine mattes; ſo that
vppon the 26. of the ſame month all our trafficke and friendſhip with them
ceaſed: but our hoaſt being our friende, came ſecretly aborde our 
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:9867:29"/> ſhips, and ſhewed vs that he and his company had two
ſhips lying before the towne, laden with Nutmegges and Mace that came from
<hi>Banda,</hi> for the which hee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed with vs at a price, vpon condition
that we ſhould ſeeme to take them by force, that thereby he might co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour
his dealing with vs: wherevpon the firſt of No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uember we ſailed cloſe to
the towne with all our ſhips, 
<note place="margin">How they tooke two Iauan ſhips</note>and ſet
vpon the two <hi>Iauan</hi> ſhippes, wherein we found to the number of 30.
ſlaues, that knew nothing of their maiſters bargaine made with vs, ſo
that they began to reſiſt vs, wherewith we ſhot among them, and
preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſlew 4. or 5. of them, the reſt leapt ouer borde, and ſwamme
to land, which done we tooke the two ſhips, and put their lading into ours: 
<note place="margin">They fought with a Portingall ſhippe.</note>The
<hi>Portingalles</hi> ſhippe that brought their Ambaſſadour, lay cloſe
vnder the ſhore, wherevnto we ſent two of our boats, but the
<hi>Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingals</hi> that were in her ſhot ſo thicke with their peeces
vppon our men, that our boates were forced to leaue them with loſſe of one
of our men, but our ſhippes ſhot in ſuch ſorte with their ordinance
vppon the <hi>Portingall</hi> ſhippe, that they ſpoyled and brake it in
peeces, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in their Captaine was ſlaine, and the victuailers that ſtil
brought vs victuailes to ſell, tolde vs that with our pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces we had ſlain
three or foure men within the towne, &amp; that the townes men began to make an
armie of ſhips to ſet vpon vs.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">They fought with a Iauan ſhippe.</note>The 2.
of Nouember we eſpyed a ſhippe that came toward <hi>Bantam,</hi> which we
ioyned vnto with our boats, and being neere vnto it, they ſpread their
fights, which were of thicke mattes, and began to defend themſelues; our men
ſhot among them with ſtone peeces and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuers, and they defended
themſelues with great cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, <pb facs="tcp:9867:30"/> hauing halfe pikes wherewith
they thruſt at vs, &amp; that ſerued likewiſe to blow arrowes out of
them, for they were like trunkes, out of the which trunkes they ſhot ſo
great numbers of arrowes, that they fell as thick as hayle, and ſhotte ſo
certainely, that therewith they hurt at the leaſt eyght or nine of our men,
but the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes are thinne and light, ſo that their blaſte coulde not make
them enter into the fleſh aboue the thicknes of two fingers, onely the head
of the arrowe (which is made of reede, and looſe ſtayeth in the fleſh)
when we ſhot with our Caliuers they runne behind their fightes, but whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they
perceiued that their matted fights could not defende them, and that they were
killed through them, they entered into their boate, and by ſtrength of oares
rowed from vs, leauing their ſhippe, wherein we founde two dead men, and we
ſlew three more of them as we rowed after their boat, ſo that in all they
loſt fiue men, as we after heard, and that they were to the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of 40.
which done, wee brought their ſhippe to ours, wherein we found good ſtore
of Ryce and dryed fiſh.</p>
            <p>The 6. of Nouember, perceyuing not any hope of more trafficke for vs
with thoſe of <hi>Bantam,</hi> wee hoiſed anker and ſet ſayle,
ſetting our courſe towardes the ſtraight of <hi>Sunda.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low them with wares.</note>The
ſeuenth of Nouember wee came and ankered before a Riuer of freſhe water,
about ſixe miles from <hi>Bantam,</hi> where wee tooke in our prouiſion of
water: thither certaine Merchants followed vs with Porſeline, telling vs that
they were ſory for our departure, &amp; that they longed for our returne
againe.</p>
            <p>The thirteenth of Nouember wee ſet ſayle, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout 
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:9867:30"/> euening wee came before <hi>Iacatra,</hi> in time paſt
called <hi>Sunda Calapa,</hi> which hath beene a rich Towne of marchandiſe,
but vppon ſome occaſions, and by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of their hard vſage the
Marchants had withdrawen themſelues from thence, therefore at this preſent
there is little or nothing to doe. <hi>Iohn Hughen</hi> in his booke ſaith
this to be the principal towne of trafficke, but that is long ſithence, for
now there is not any trade of mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandiſe.</p>
            <p>The fourteenth of Nouember wee ſent two of our men into the towne,
hauing ſome of theirs in pawne, who tolde vs that many of the inhabitantes
were gone out of the towne with all their goodes, being in great feare of our
peeces, and there wee had great ſtore of victuailes, and much more then wee
required brought abord our ſhips.</p>
            <p>The 18. wee ſet ſaile from <hi>Iacatra,</hi> and being about two
miles from the towne, our ſhippe called <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterdam</hi> fell vppon a
cliffe, but it got off againe without any hurt, and therewith wee preſently
made towardes the ſtraight.</p>
            <p>The 2. of December we paſſed by 3. townes which we might
eaſily perceiue, we likewiſe paſſed by <hi>Tubam,</hi> and ankered
vnder <hi>Sidaya.</hi> The 3. of December there came men out of the towne,
&amp; deſired vs to ſtay, ſaying that there we might haue Cloues &amp;
Nutmegs as many as we woulde, bringing certaine banketting ſtuffe (as a
preſent from their King) vnto <hi>Sche<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lengers</hi> ſhip, becauſe it lay neareſt to the land, and
they came moſt abord it.</p>
            <p>The 4. of December they came again into <hi>Schellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers</hi>
ſhip, bringing certaine preſentes with them, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the reſt a
certayne birde that coulde ſwallowe <pb facs="tcp:9867:31"/> fyer, which is a very
ſtrange fowle, and was brought a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liue to <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> which after
was giuen to the ſtates of <hi>Hollande</hi> lying in the <hi>Hage,</hi> and
ſome good fruites, willing vs to ſende a man on ſhore to ſee their
ſpices, whereof they ſaid they had great ſtore: wherevpon we ſent a man
out of the <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> and with him an inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preter, one of the
<hi>Portingalles</hi> ſlaues, they leauing three or foure of their men aborde
our ſhippes, for pawnes till his returne: when our man came to lande hee was
well vſed, and there they ſhewed him fortie or fiftie bals of Cloues; which
done they brought him before the King, that promiſed him great fauor, and
told him that the next day he wold himſelfe come aborde our ſhips, and
deale with our Captaines, and with that he let our man depart.</p>
            <p>The 5. of December we expected the Kinges com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming aborde, putting
out all our flagges and ſtreamers, and about noone there came 8. or 9.
indifferent great ſhippes full of men from off the ſhore, wherein wee
thought the King to bee, but when they were almoſt at vs they diuided
themſelues, three of them rowing to <hi>Shellengers</hi> ſhip, and when
they borded him, they thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the King had been there, <hi>Reymer van
Hel</hi> as Factor and the Maiſter came forth to receyue him, but the
<hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers</hi> entering all at once, <hi>Reymer van Hel</hi> ſaid, What
will all theſe people doe aborde the ſhippe, for there was at the leaſt
two hundred men, who all at one time drewe out their poinyardes, and ſtabbed
our men that neuer ſuſpected them, ſo that preſently they had ſlaine
twelue of the ſhippe, and two ſore wounded, that boldly with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoode them:
the reſt of our men being vnder hatches preſently tooke their pikes, and
thruſt ſo faſt out at the <pb n="29" facs="tcp:9867:31"/> grates, 
<note place="margin">How the Indians be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note>that the
<hi>Iauers</hi> woulde haue forced the middle part of the ſhip, wherein was
two entries, but our men ſtanding at them with their ſwordes in hande draue
them out, not ceaſing ſtill to thruſt vp with their pikes, meane time
they kindled fier, lighted their matches, &amp; ſhot off their ſtone peeces
that lay aboue the hatches, wherwith they began preſently to flie, moſt of
them lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping ouer bord, and ſwam to their two boates, that lay harde by our
ſhippes, whereof one with a great peece was preſently ſtriken in peeces:
The reſt of our ſhips hearing vs ſhoote in that manner, entered into
their boats, and made towardes them, rowing harde to the three <hi>Indian</hi>
fuſtes, wherein were at the leaſt 100. men, and ſhotte among them with
their peeces, wherewith they leapt into the water, euery man ſwimming to
ſhore, and we with two boates after them, hewing and killing them as our
deadly enemies, who vnder pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of friendſhippe ſought to murther vs,
and wee handled them in ſuch ſort, that of two hundred men there got not
aboue thirty of them to lande, the reſt of their fuſtes lay farre off and
beheld the fight: Three of their fuſtes thought to rowe to the Pinace to take
her, which they might eaſily haue done, as hauing not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue 7. or 8. men in
her, being buſie to ſet vppe a newe maſte, but when they perceyued their
men to bee ſo handeled in the <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> and that they leapt ouer
borde, they turned backe againe, and in great haſte ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed to land, ſo that
at that time they got not much by the bargaine, and no ſmall griefe to vs,
for there wee loſt 12. men, that were all ſtabbed with poinyards, their
names were <hi>Iohn Iacobſon Schellenger,</hi> maiſter of the ſhip,
<hi>Reymer van hel</hi> Factor, <hi>Gielis Gieleſon</hi> Gentleman,
<hi>Barent <pb facs="tcp:9867:32"/> 
                  <note place="margin">The names of their men that were
ſtab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</note>Bonteboter, Arent Cornedrager, Cornelis van Alcmuer, Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
Ianſon, Wiltſchut Ioos</hi> the Carpenter, <hi>Adrian de
Metſelar,</hi> one of the <hi>Portingalles</hi> ſlaues, and two boyes,
whereof one was but twelue yeares olde, whereby wee perceyued them to be a
kinde of cruell people, for they had giuen the little boy and all the reſt of
our men at the leaſt 12. ſtabbes a peece after they were dead.</p>
            <p>The ſame day about euening we hoyſed ankers, and ſet ſaile,
hauing manned the <hi>Amſterdam</hi> with men out of our other ſhippes, and
ſo helde our courſe Eaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward.</p>
            <p>The 6. of December we came to a great Iſland cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<hi>Madura,</hi> where we ankered, and in the euening two of their men came
aborde our ſhippes, with meſſage from their Gouernour, ſaying that we
were welcome, deſiring vs to ſtay there, for he would trafficke with vs,
and ſell vs ſome Pepper, as they ſaide, but wee belieued them not.</p>
            <p>The 7. of December there came another boat abord, bringing certaine
fruites, ſaying that the next day their Gouernour would come to ſee our
ſhippes.</p>
            <p>The 8. there came a great fuſte and three ſmal boats, from off
the land all full of men, ſaying their Gouernor was among them: we willed
them not to goe to the <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> but to the <hi>Mauritius,</hi> but
they woulde not, but made to the <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> thinking becauſe there
had beene ſo many murthered in her, there was not ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny men aborde her at
that time, and when they were within a pykes length of her, (although they were
di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected to the other ſhippes) they remembring their late miſchance,
ſhotte off three or foure ſtone Peeces full laden, wherewith they ſlew
and hurt many of the <pb n="30" facs="tcp:9867:32"/> 
               <hi>Indians,</hi> wherevpon they
preſently leapt ouer bord, &amp; wee with our boates followed after and
ſlew diuers of them, taking ten or twelue, thinking by them to know what
their intent was to doe, but they coulde not cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie vs, and therefore we let
them go againe onely kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping two boyes, who long after ſtole out of the
ſhippe, and ſwamme to lande: They tolde vs that the Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour being a
Biſhoppe or chiefe inſtructor of the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, was within the boate and
ſlaine among the reſt, hee had therein likewiſe a little boy one of his
ſonnes who wee likewiſe tooke, and ſent to lande: The Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoppe was of
<hi>Meca,</hi> and much eſteemed of among them, a great Clearke, and
Gouernour ouer all the reſt of the Countrey: There was a Iewell found about
him, which as yet is kept.</p>
            <p>About euening we hoyſed ankers, &amp; ſet ſayle, &amp; the 11.
of December we came to two ſmall Iſlands, where wee ankered, there wee
founde none but poore people and fiſhermen, that brought vs fiſh, Hens,
&amp; other fruit to ſell.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">How farre they were from
<hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luccas</hi>
               </note>The 13. wee ſet ſayle, and the 14. wee had a
Weſt winde, which they call the paſſage winde, that would haue ſerued
vs well to ſaile to <hi>Moluccas,</hi> from whence wee were not diſtant
aboue two hundred miles, and as then it was a good yeare for Cloues, which
happeneth euery three yeares: It was told vs that we might there haue a Cabbin
laden full of Cloues, wherevpon wee determined to ſayle thither, but
becauſe wee had already indured a long and troubleſome voyage, and but ill
manned, wee woulde not, longing to bee at home: This contrary wind holding
vppon the foure and twentie of December wee came to an Iſlande <pb facs="tcp:9867:33"/>
where we had beene before.</p>
            <p>The 25. of December <hi>Iohn Molenaer</hi> maiſter of the
<hi>Mauritius,</hi> dyed ſodainely, for an hower before hee was well and in
good health.</p>
            <p>The 28. 29. 30. and 31. of December wee were buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to take all
the wares, ſayles and other thinges out of the <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> her
victuailes and furnitures ſeruing for our voyage homewarde, &amp; lying vnder
that Iſland, we had victuailes brought vs euery day as much as wee needed,
both fiſh, Hens, veniſon and fruit, and at reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable price, but there
we could get no water.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterdam ſet on fire.</note>The 11. of
Ianuary when we had vnladen the <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterdam</hi> we ſet her on fier,
letting her burne, taking her men into our ſhippes.</p>
            <p>The 12. of Ianuarie we ſet ſayle again, ſome deſiring to
ſayle Eaſtward, others Weſtward, but in fine wee ſet Weſtwarde to
ſayle once againe to <hi>Bantam,</hi> wherewith the <hi>Mauritius</hi>
ſayled Southeaſtwarde, to gette about the Iſland of <hi>Iaua,</hi> and we
followed her. The 14. of Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuary we once againe perceyued the Eaſt point of
the Iſland of <hi>Madura,</hi> and held our courſe Southward: on that
ſide of <hi>Madura</hi> there lyeth many ſmall Iſlandes, through which we
ſayled.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Pinace on ground.</note>The 16. in the
morning our Pinace fell on grounde vpon the coaſt of <hi>Iaua,</hi> not far
from <hi>Pannorocan,</hi> where ſhe ſhotte off three peeces, at the which
warning wee made thither with our boates, and by the helpe of God got her off
againe: There we ſaw a high hil that burnt, vnder and aboue the fire hauing a
great ſmoake, moſt ſtrange to behold.</p>
            <p>The 18. of Ianuary we entered into the ſtraight that runneth
betweene <hi>Iaua</hi> and <hi>Baly,</hi> and by reaſon of the 
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:9867:33"/> hard &amp; contrary ſtreame that ran therin, we were
forced to anker vpon the coaſt of <hi>Iaua,</hi> where wee found good anker
ground.</p>
            <p>The 19. wee ſet ſayle, and when wee came neere to the coaſt of
<hi>Baly,</hi> we entered into a rough ſtreame, and our ſhippes draue
backeward, as ſwiftly as an arrow out of a bow, and there we found no anker
ground, nor a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny anker could haue holden vs, but <hi>Molenaer</hi> got the
coaſt of <hi>Iaua</hi> and ankered, which in the ende wee like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe did,
and ankered at the leaſt three miles from him, and ſo much we had driuen
backe in the ſpace of halfe an houre.</p>
            <p>The 20. of Ianuarie wee went and lay by our other ſhips.</p>
            <p>The 21. of Ianuarie there came two barkes to the <hi>Mauritius,</hi>
wherein there was one that coulde ſpeake good <hi>Portingall,</hi> who tolde
vs that the towne of <hi>Balla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boam</hi> was beſieged by a ſtrange King,
that had marryed the King of <hi>Ballaboams</hi> daughter, and after he had
laine with her he cauſed her to bee ſlaine, and then came to beſiege her
father. This towne of <hi>Ballaboam</hi> lyeth on the Eaſt end of the
Iſland of <hi>Iaua,</hi> and is the ſame towne where M. <hi>Candiſh</hi>
was when hee paſſed that way, and the old King wherof he writeth was as
then yet liuing, being at the leaſt 160. years of age. There we ſaw great
numbers of Battes, that flew ouer our ſhippes, and were as bigge as Crowes,
which in that Countrey they vſe to eat, as they ſay: About noone we came
before the towne of <hi>Ballaboam,</hi> ſo neare vnto it that we might
eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſee it, and there we lay behind a high point of lande, thinking to
take in water.</p>
            <p>The 22. of Ianuarie we tooke our Pinace, and ſayled <pb facs="tcp:9867:34"/>
about the ſhore as neere the land as poſſible we might, to ſeeke for
freſh water, but we found none, for the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer that ran through the towne was
paled vp (by them that lay before it) ſo that no man might paſſe either
out or in, but onely on the lande ſide, and that with great daunger: The
ſame day there came 2. or 3. men abord our ſhippe, that ſtole out of the
towne by night, and came from the King, to deſire our help with our great
ſhot, which wee coulde not doe; becauſe that therea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouts it was very
ſhallow, and we might not go neere it with our ſhippes: they tolde vs they
had great want of victuailes within the towne, whereby many of them were
already deade for hunger, and much deſired our aide, but it was not in vs to
doe. Thoſe that beſieged the towne were <hi>Mores,</hi> but they in the
towne were hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens, and as yet had not receyued <hi>Mahomets</hi> lawe, and
that (as wee heard after) was the cauſe of their warre: There wee ſawe many
Storkes flying and ſitting in the fielde: with vs we cannot imagaine where
the Storkes remaine in winter time, but here wee ſawe them in the winter
time.</p>
            <p>The 24. of Ianuarie we ſayled from thence, percey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing nothing for
vs to get, and tooke our courſe right ouer to the Iſland of
<hi>Bally.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 25. we came to <hi>Bally,</hi> where one of their barks borded
vs, telling vs that there we ſhould find a Riuer of freſh water, and of all
thinges els ſufficient to ſerue our neceſſities, wherevpon wee
ankered.</p>
            <p>The 26. of Ianuarie our Pinace ſent her boat to land, to ſee the
Riuer, and there one of our men was ſent on ſhore, but when he was on land
he found nothing, but an armie of ten thouſand men, that ment to relieue the 
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:9867:34"/> towne of <hi>Ballaboam,</hi> and the Riuer was nothing
worth to lade water, wherevpon our men came on borde a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine: Their Generall
thought to haue gotten ſome great pray out of our ſhippes.</p>
            <p>The 27. of Ianuarie we ſet ſayle to finde a conueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent place to
refreſh vs with water and other prouiſion, for wee were informed by a man
of <hi>Bengala,</hi> that of his owne will ſayled with vs, and that had beene
in <hi>Bally,</hi> that there wee ſhould finde water and other thinges to
ſerue our neceſſities, ſo that by night wee ankered vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a high
pointe of lande on the South weſt ende of <hi>Bally.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 28. of Ianuary one of their boates borded vs with ſixe or
ſeuen men, ſaying that their King was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous to deale with vs for
ſuch wares as hee had, and ſent to know from whence we came, and we ſaide
wee came out of <hi>Holland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 29. and 30. there came more men aborde our ſhippes, but as wee
ſuſpected that was not the right ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, for the people came rowing in
great haſte a far off, and the man of <hi>Bengala</hi> could not tell what to
ſay, but the King was thereabout, and euery day ſent vs ſome fruit.</p>
            <p>The firſt of February wee had two hogges brought aborde our
ſhippes, that wee bought for two Ryalles of eyght, and we eate them very
ſauerly.</p>
            <p>The 2. of Februarie, we ſet ſaile that wee might get aboue the
point, where wee thought to finde a better place for freſhe water, but by
reaſon the winde was contrary, wee coulde not doe it, but were forced to
an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker againe.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:9867:35"/>The <hi>3.</hi> of February we ſet ſaile againe,
and then wee had a ſtorme, ſo that our ſaile blew euery way, and
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the contrarie winde we could not reach aboue the point, but were
conſtrained to anker, but the <hi>Mau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritius</hi> and the Pinace got paſt
it, although thereby the <hi>Mauritius</hi> was in no little daunger; but
becauſe the Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lot had laid a wager of 6. Rialles of 8. that hee woulde get
aboue it, hee would paſſe, what daunger ſoeuer it might be, and ſayled
cloſe along by the cliffes, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by wee lay at anker without companie.</p>
            <p>The 4. and 5. wee ſet ſaile once againe to get aboue the point
but could not reach it.</p>
            <p>The 6. we had a letter from <hi>Rodenburgh,</hi> that certifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vs
how the <hi>Mauritius</hi> lay at anker at the leaſt 7. or 8. miles beyond
the point, and he that brought the letter came with it ouer land; and at the
ſame time there was a man ſent on lande with a ſmall preſent for the
King, that we might winne his fauour.</p>
            <p>The 7. our man came on borde againe, and brought vs newes how
<hi>Rodenburgh</hi> with one of the <hi>Portingalles</hi> ſlaues, being on
lande were againſt their willes led be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the King, but the ſaylors of
the <hi>Mauritius</hi> had got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten men for pledges.</p>
            <p>The 8. of Ianuarie, the ſame man went on land out of our ſhippe
with more preſentes of veluet and a cali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, the better to get the Kinges
fauour, which liked him well, and deſired vs to bring the ſhip nearer to
the towne, ſaying he would ſend vs water and other things ſufficient to
ſupply our wants.</p>
            <p>The 9. we ſayled into the cheeke with our ſhippe, &amp; ankered
about a ſmall halfe mile from the land, &amp; being ankered there came at the
leaſt 70. boates of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie <pb n="33" facs="tcp:9867:35"/> to ſee our ſhip,
and the King ſent vs word that hee was deſirous to heare vs ſhoote off 5.
or 6. of our great peeces, wherevppon wee ſhot fiue of our greateſt
pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and the King ſtoode vppon the ſhore to ſee them.</p>
            <p>The 10. we had a letter from <hi>Cornelis Houtman,</hi> to wil vs to
come to them, for that there they had founde a good place for water, and of all
other neceſſaries, ſo that about euening wee ſet ſayle, leauing two
of our men and a <hi>Portingall</hi> ſlaue among the <hi>Indians,</hi> whome
the King promiſed ſhould come vnto vs ouer land, yet that night wee could
not reach aboue the point, meane time we perceyued our Pinace that came to
helpe vs.</p>
            <p>The 16. we got by the <hi>Mauritius,</hi> that had already laden in
her water, and hooped her veſſels, wherevpon we began preſently to do the
like, and to viſite our veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels that were almoſt ſpoyled.</p>
            <p>The 17. our men whome wee left with the King came ouer land vnto our
ſhippes, and then we bought great ſtore of cattle and fruit.</p>
            <p>The 18. 19. 20. and 21. wee imployed our time to lade water, which
wee had verie eaſily, and refreſhed our ſelues with Cattle, Hogges,
fruit, and Lemons ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient. There came one of the Kinges principall
offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers with our men ouer land, to pleaſure vs in all things we deſired,
he was very deſirous to haue ſome preſent of vs.</p>
            <p>The 22. of Ianuarie two of our men that ſayled in the
<hi>Mauritius</hi> ſtayed on lande, but wee knewe not the cauſe: it
ſhould ſeeme ſome great promiſes had beene made vnto them, for as we
vnderſtoode, the King was very deſirous to haue all ſortes of ſtrange
nations about <pb facs="tcp:9867:36"/> him, 
<note place="margin">Two of our men ſtayed with the
<hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians.</hi>
               </note>but our people were therein much ouerſeene, for
there they liued among heathens, that neyther knewe God nor his commandementes,
it appeared that their youthes and wilde heades did not remember it, one of
their names was <hi>Emanuel Rodenburgh</hi> of <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> the other
<hi>Iacob Cuyper</hi> of <hi>Delft:</hi> within a day or two they ſent vnto
vs for their clothes, but wee ſent them not.</p>
            <p>The 23. 24. and 25. we made a voyage on land, and fetcht as many
Hogges abord our ſhippes as we could eate.</p>
            <p>The 25. of Februarie we hoyſed ankers, minding to ſet ſaile
&amp; ſo go homeward, leauing our 2. men aforeſaid on land, but becauſe
it was calme weather we ankered, and went once againe on lande, and the 26. of
the ſame Month wee ſet ſaile and helde our courſe Weſt South weſt,
but we had a calme.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <head>The ſituation of the Iſland of Baly.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Iſland of <hi>Baly</hi> lying at the Eaſt end of
<hi>Iaua,</hi> is a verie fruitfull Iſlande of Ryce, Hennes, Hogges, that are
verie good, and great ſtore of cattle: but they are very drie and leane
beaſtes. They haue many horſes: the inhabitantes are heathens and haue no
religion, for ſome pray to Kine, others to the Sunne, and euerie man as hee
thinketh good. 
<note place="margin">How 50. women burnt them ſelues with one
man.</note>When a man dyeth his wife burneth her ſelfe with him: there were
ſome of their men aborde our ſhippes, that told vs, that when ſome man
dyeth in that Countrey, that ſometimes there are at the leaſt fifty wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men 
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:9867:36"/> that will burne themſelues with him, and ſhe that doth
not ſo is accounted for a diſhoneſt woman: ſo that it is a common thing
with them: The apparel both of men and women is for the moſt part like
thoſe of <hi>Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam,</hi> nothing but a cloth about their middles: Their
weapons is, each man a poinyarde at their backes, and a trunke with an iron
point like a ſpeare, about a fadom and a halfe long, out of the which they
blowe certaine arrowes, whereof they haue a caſe full; it is an euil wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon
for naked men: they are enemies to the <hi>Mores</hi> and
<hi>Portingalles.</hi> This Iſland yeeldeth no ſpice, nor any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
coſtly ware, onely victuailes and clothes which they weare about their
bodies, and ſlaues that are there to be ſolde. The King went with more
ſtate then the King of <hi>Bantam:</hi> all his garde had pikes with heades
of fine gold, and he ſate in a wagon that was drawen by 2. two white
Buffles.</p>
            <p>The firſt of March we had a calme.</p>
            <p>The third we got a good wind that blew Southeaſt, holding our
courſe Weſt South weſt.</p>
            <p>The fourteenth the wind blew ſtil South eaſt, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times more
Southwarde, and ſometimes Eaſtward, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vnder 14. degrees, and a good
ſharpe gale, holding our courſe Weſt Southweſt: 
<note place="margin">The ſituati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Iaua</hi>
               </note>There we
found that <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ua</hi> is not ſo broade, nor ſtretcheth it ſelfe not
ſo much Southwarde, as it is ſet dovvne in the Carde: for if it were, we
ſhould haue paſſed clean through the middle of the land.</p>
            <p>The 22. of March the winde helde as it did, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vnder 19.
degrees, holding our courſe Weſt South weſt.</p>
            <p>The 19. of April our ſhip had no more bread left, but <pb facs="tcp:9867:37"/> for our laſt partition euery man had ſeuen pound, both good and
badde breade, and from that time forwarde our meate was Rice ſodden in water,
and euery man had a canne of water euery day, with three romers of wine, and
weekely each man three romers or glaſſes of oyle and that very ſtrong,
and nothing els.</p>
            <p>The 20. we had a calme, the <hi>21.</hi> a calme with a Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therne
aire.</p>
            <p>The 23. a good wind that blew Southweſt.</p>
            <p>The 24. we ſaw the firme lande of <hi>Aethiopia,</hi> being vnder
33 degrees, and as wee geſſed, wee were then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout an hundred miles from
the Cape <hi>de bona Sperance,</hi> yet we thought we had been at the leaſt
three hundred miles from it, ſo that wee may ſay, that God wrought
wonderfully for vs: for that if wee had fallen by night vpon the land, we had
ſurely runne vpon it: wee had a good winde out of the Weſt, and Weſt
Southweſt.</p>
            <p>The 25. of Aprill in the morning wee had a calme, with a very hollow
water, &amp; at euening we had a good winde, that came North and Northeaſt,
and although wee had ſo good a vvind yet our ſhippe bare but little
ſayle, although the other two ſhippes of our company were at the leaſt
two mile before vs, for moſt part of the night wee ſayled with our
ſchouer ſaile, holding our courſe Southweſt &amp; by Weſt.</p>
            <p>The 26. of Aprill in the morning we coulde not ſee our ſhippes,
which pleaſed not our men, beſides that our ſhippe was very weake,
whereby her ribs ſhoke, and her ioynts with the force of the water opened and
ſhut, ſo that as then our ſhippe was very leake, hauing the winde
Northweſt, holding our courſe as neere as wee could Weſt Southweſt, and
then we put out our maine <pb n="35" facs="tcp:9867:37"/> ſayles, at noone the winde
came Weſt, with a great ſtorme, ſo that moſt of our ſayles blew in
peeces, and ſo wee draue forward with out ſayles.</p>
            <p>The 27. of Aprill ſtill driuing without ſayle with a Weſt
winde, wee were vnder thirty ſixe degrees, ſo that we found that the
ſtreame draue vs South &amp; South Weſt.</p>
            <p>The 28. of Aprill ſtill driuing without ſailes, we had the
height of 36. degrees and 20. minutes, and about euening we hoiſed ſaile
againe, the winde being Weſt Southweſt, &amp; we held our courſe
Northweſt with ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry hollow water.</p>
            <p>The 29. of April we could not as yet ſee our ſhippes, the wind
being Weſt.</p>
            <p>The <hi>30.</hi> of Aprill we had fayre weather with a Weſt and
weſt South weſt wind, and then we ſaw many great birdes with white
billes, which is a ſigne not to bee far from the Cape <hi>de bona
Sperance,</hi> we likewiſe ſaw certain ſmall birdes, ſpeckled on their
backes, and white vpon their breaſts.</p>
            <p>The firſt of May wee had a South vvinde with fayre weather, hauing
<hi>34.</hi> degrees and a halfe, holding our courſe Weſt Southweſt.</p>
            <p>The ſeconde of May wee vvere vnder <hi>35.</hi> degrees, and
½. holding our courſe Weſt and Weſt and by North.</p>
            <p>The fourth of May we found our ſelues to be vnder <hi>37.</hi>
degrees South South eaſt winde, our courſe being Weſt and by North, and
Weſt North weſt.</p>
            <p>The 5. and 6. of May we had all one winde at noone being vnder
<hi>35.</hi> degrees, wee thought wee had paſt the Cape, and held our
courſe Northweſt, towardes Saint <pb facs="tcp:9867:38"/> 
               <hi>Helena,</hi> ſtill
without ſight of our ſhips.</p>
            <p>The 8. of May with a South wind wee helde North Weſt and by
Weſt.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Signes of the Cape <hi>de bona
Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranza.</hi>
               </note>The 9. we had a calme with a gray sky, and were vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
31. degrees and twentie minutes, and then our por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of oyle was increaſed
a glaſſe more euery weeke, ſo that euery man had foure glaſſes.</p>
            <p>The <hi>10.</hi> we had ſtil ſouth winds, &amp; were vnder 29.
deg.</p>
            <p>The 14. of Aprill twice or thrice we ſaw reedes, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<hi>Trombos</hi> driuing on the water, being ſuch as driue about the Cape
<hi>de bona Speranza,</hi> which wee thought verie ſtrange, for that the
<hi>Portingals</hi> write, that they are ſeene but thirtie myles from the
Cape, and wee geſt our ſelues to be at the leaſt 200. beyond it.</p>
            <p>The 15. we ſtill had a South eaſt wind, &amp; helde our courſe
Northweſt.</p>
            <p>The 16. of Aprill in the morning we ſaw two ſhips, whereat we
much reioyced, thinking they had beene our companie, we made to leewarde of
them, and the ſmalleſt of them comming ſomewhat neere vs, about the
length of the ſhotte of a great peece, ſhee made pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently toward her
fellow, whereby we perceiued them to bee French men, yet wee kept to leeward,
thinking they would haue come &amp; ſpoken with vs, but it ſhould ſeeme
they feared vs, and durſt not come, but held their courſe Northeaſt: at
noone we had the height of 22. de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, and 50. minutes with a Southeaſt
wind, holding our courſe Northweſt.</p>
            <p>The 17. of May wee were vnder <hi>21.</hi> degrees and a halfe: the
18. the wind being Southerly, we vvere vnder 19. degrees and a halfe.</p>
            <p>The 19. and <hi>20.</hi> we had a calme with a Southern are.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>map of St Helena</figDesc>
               <head>SANCTA HELENA</head>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:9867:39"/>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:9867:39"/>The 21. the ayre comming
Southweſt, we held our courſe Northweſt, and were vnder 17. degrees and
⅔. partes: There we found the compaſſe to decline three quarters of
a ſtrike or line North eaſtward, after noone we had a Southeaſt wind, and
our courſe Weſt North<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weſt.</p>
            <p>The 22. of May we had ſtill a Southeaſt winde, and were vnder
the height of 16. degrees and 40. minutes, holding our courſe Weſt
Northweſt.</p>
            <p>The 23. of May, by reaſon of the cloudy sky, about noone we could
not take the height of the Sunne, but as we geſt we had the height of the
Iſland of <hi>S. Helena,</hi> and held our courſe Weſt and by South to
keepe vnder that height, for there the compaſſes decline a whole ſtrike
or line: in the euening we found that we were vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der 16. degrees.</p>
            <p>The 24. of May in the morning wee diſcouered a <hi>Portingall</hi>
ſhip, that ſtayed for vs, and put out a flagge of truce, and becauſe our
flagge of truce was not ſo readie as theirs, and we hauing the wind of him,
therefore he ſhot two ſhootes at vs, and put forth a flagge out of his
maine top, and we ſhot 5. or 6. times at him, and ſo held on our courſe
without ſpeaking to him, hauing a South eaſt winde, holding our courſe
Weſt and by South to find the Iſland of <hi>S. Helena,</hi> which the
<hi>Portingal</hi> likewiſe ſought.</p>
            <p>The 25. of May we diſcouered the Iſland of <hi>S. Hele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi>
but we could not ſee the <hi>Portingal</hi> ſhip, ſtill ſayling with a
ſtiffe Southeaſt wind, &amp; about euening we were vnder the Iſland,
which is very high lande, and may be ſeene at the leaſt <hi>14.</hi> or
<hi>15.</hi> miles off, and as we ſayled a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the North point, there lay
three other great <hi>Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingal</hi> ſhips, we being not aboue half a mile
from them, <pb facs="tcp:9867:40"/> wherevpon wee helde in the weather and to ſeawarde
Northeaſt as much as we might. 
<note place="margin">Foure Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingal ſhips richly laden</note>The
<hi>Portingalles</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyuing vs, the Admiral of their fleet ſhot off a
peece to call their men that were on land to come a borde, and then wee ſaw
foure of their ſhippes together, that were worth a great ſumme of money, at
the leaſt 300. tunnes of gold, for they were all laden with ſpices,
precious ſtones, and other rich wares, and therefore wee durſt not anker
vnder the Iſland, but lay all night Northeaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde, ſtaying for our
company.</p>
            <p>The 26. of May in the morning wee made towardes the Iſland againe,
with a good Southeaſt winde, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout noone or ſomewhat paſt we
diſcried two ſhippes, and about euening as we made towards them, we knew
them to be our company, which made vs to reioice, for we had been aſunder the
ſpace of a whole Month, &amp; ſo we helde together and ſayled homeward,
holding our courſe Northweſt: for as yet our men were well and in good
health, and we found a good Southeaſt winde, and had water enough for foure
or fiue monthes.</p>
            <p>The 27. 28. 29. and 30. of May wee had a Southeaſt winde, with
faire weather, and the 27. day we were vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der 14. degrees, The firſt of Iune
we were vnder 6. de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, with a Southeſt wind, holding our courſe north
weſt, but by means of the Compaſſe that yeelded north eaſtward, we kept
about Northvveſt &amp; by North. The 6. of Iune vve were vnder one degree on
the South ſide of the line, there vvee founde that the ſtreame draue vs
faſt into the Weſt, and therefore vvee helde our courſe more Northernely,
and ſayled Northvveſt &amp; by north, vvith an Eaſt and South eaſt
vvind. 
<note place="margin">They paſt the Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noctial line.</note>The 7. of
Iune wee paſt the Equinoctiall line, vvith an Eaſt vvinde, holding our
courſe North Northvveſt.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:9867:40"/>The 10. of Iune in the euening we were vnder 5.
de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees and a halfe on the North ſide of the line, and then we began again
to ſee the north ſtar, which for the ſpace of 2. years we had not
ſeene, holding our courſe North Northweſt, there we began to haue ſmal
blaſts, &amp; ſome times calmes, but the aire all South and
Southeaſt.</p>
            <p>The <hi>11.</hi> of Iune we had a calme, and yet a darke sky, that
came Southeaſtwarde. The <hi>12.</hi> of Iune wee had a cloſe sky with
raine, and the ſame day about euening our fore top maſte fell downe.</p>
            <p>The 13. we ſtrake all our ſailes and mended our ſhip.</p>
            <p>The <hi>14.</hi> we had the wind Northward, holding our courſe
Weſt Northweſt as neare as we coulde, but by reaſon of the thick sky wee
could not take height of the Sun. The <hi>15.</hi> of Iune we had the wind
North, &amp; North Northweſt. The <hi>16.</hi> of Iune wee had the height of
9. degrees &amp; <hi>10.</hi> minutes, the winde being Northeaſt and North
Northeaſt. The <hi>17.</hi> the winde was Northeaſt with fair weather,
&amp; we held Northweſt, &amp; northweſt &amp; by North till after noone. 
<note place="margin">They tooke a great fiſh.</note>The <hi>18.</hi>
we tooke a great fiſh called an <hi>Aluercoor,</hi> which ſerued vs all for
2. meals, which wee had not taſted of long time before.</p>
            <p>The 26. we had ſtill a Northeaſt winde, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times larger,
holding our courſe North Northweſt with large ſaile, and were vnder
<hi>17.</hi> degrees and ½.</p>
            <p>The ſame day there came much duſt flying into our ſhippe, as
if we had paſt hard by ſome ſandie downe, &amp; we geſt the neareſt
land to vs might be the Iſland of <hi>S. Anthony,</hi> and wee were as then
at the leaſt 40. or 50. miles from it: The ſame day likewiſe there came a
fly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing fiſh into our ſhippe, which we eat.</p>
            <p>The 28. of Iune wee had the height of 20. degrees, with a Eaſt
Northeaſt wind &amp; Eaſt and by Weſt, with <pb facs="tcp:9867:41"/> full ſayle,
there we ſaw much Sargoſſe, driuing on the water. The laſt of Iune we
had the Sun right ouer our heades, and yet we felt no heat, for that by
reaſon of the cold ayre we had a fine coole weather. The ſame day we
paſſed <hi>Tropicus Cancri,</hi> ſtill hauing the winde Eaſt
Northeaſt, and in the euening we were vnder 24. degr.</p>
            <p>The ſecond of Iuly we ſtill ſaw Sargoſſe driuing vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the
water, &amp; had the wind ſomewhat lower North Northeaſt with a calme. The
thirde of Iuly the winde came againe Eaſt Northeaſt, and wee helde our
courſe North and by Weſt. The 8. of Iuly wee were vnder 33. degrees &amp;
½. with an Eaſt wind, holding our courſe North and by Eaſt, and
yet we ſaw much Sargoſſe dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, but not ſo thicke as it did
before.</p>
            <p>The 10. of Iuly we had a good wind that blew ſouth and South and
by Eaſt, and hoyſted vp our maine tops, that for the ſpace of 26. daies
were neuer touched, and held our courſe North Northeaſt, there we were in
no little feare to fall among the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> fleet, which at that time
of the yeare keepeth about the <hi>Flemmiſh</hi> Iſlands.</p>
            <p>The ſame day one of our boyes fell ouer bord, and was carried away
with a ſwift ſtreame before the wind, but to his great good fortune, the
Pinace ſaued him, that was at the leaſt a quarter of a mile from vs: this
euening we found the height of 36. degrees.</p>
            <p>The 12. of Iuly we had a Southweſt wind, holding our courſe
Northeaſt and by North: Our Pilot and the Pilot of the Pinnace differed a
degree in the height of the Sunne, for ours had 38. degrees, and theirs but 37.
We geſt to be about the Iſlands of <hi>Corbo</hi> &amp; <hi>Flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res,</hi>
but the one held more eaſterly, and the other more Weſterly. The 13. of
Iuly wee had ſtill a Southweſt winde, and after noone wee thought wee had
ſeene <pb n="39" facs="tcp:9867:41"/> land, but we were not aſſured thereof, for it
was ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what cloſe. The 14. of Iuly we had a calme, and ſaw no land, and
then our men began to be ſicke.</p>
            <p>The 17. of Iuly wee had a South Southeaſt winde, with faire
weather, and were vnder 41. degrees, holding our courſe Eaſt
Northeaſt.</p>
            <p>The <hi>18. 19. 20.</hi> and <hi>21.</hi> it was calme. The 22. of
Iuly the winde came North, and wee helde our courſe Eaſt Southeaſt. The
23. of Iuly the wind was North North eaſt and Northeaſt, and we held as
near as we could Eaſt &amp; Eaſt Southeaſt, the ſame day our ſteward
found a bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell of ſtockfiſh in the roming, which if we had beene at home
we would haue caſt it on the dunghil, it ſtunke ſo filthily, &amp; yet we
eat it as ſauerly as the beſt meat in the world.</p>
            <p>The 24. we had a Weſt wind, &amp; that with ſo ſtrong a gale,
that wee were forced to ſet two men at helme, which pleaſed vs well.</p>
            <p>The 25. of Iuly we had a ſtorme that blew Weſt and weſt
Northweſt, ſo that we bare but two ſailes, holding our courſe
Northeaſt and by Eaſt.</p>
            <p>The firſt of Auguſt we were vnder 45. degrees with a North
weſt wind, holding our courſe Northeaſt and by Eaſt.</p>
            <p>The ſecond of Auguſt one of our men called <hi>Gerrit
Corneliſon</hi> of <hi>Spijckenes</hi> died, being the firſt man that dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
in our voyage homeward.</p>
            <p>The 4. of Auguſt we had a Northweſt wind.</p>
            <p>The 5. of Auguſt in the morning the winde came Southweſt, and we
were vnder 47. degrees, holding our courſe Northeaſt and the North
Northeaſt, and wee geſt that vvee vvere not farre from the channell,
thoſe dayes aforeſaid vve had ſo great colde in our ſhippes, as 
<pb facs="tcp:9867:42"/> if it had beene in the middle of winter: We could not be warme
with all the clothes wee had. The ſame day we ſaw Sargoſſe driue vpon
the water.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">They ſaw a ſhippe with the Prince of Prince
of Oranges flagge.</note>The 6. of Auguſt we had a Weſt wind, in the
mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning caſt out our lead and found grounde at 80. fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and about noone
we ſaw a ſhippe that bare the Princes flagge, yet durſt not come neare
vs, although we made ſignes vnto him, and after noone wee ſaw the land of
<hi>Heiſſant,</hi> whereat we all reioyced.</p>
            <p>The 7. of Auguſt in the morning we ſaw the land of
<hi>Fraunce,</hi> and held our courſe North northeaſt, and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe vve
ſaw a ſmall ſhippe, but ſpake not vvith it.</p>
            <p>The 8. of Auguſt in the morning vve ſavv the Kiskas, and had a
South vvind and ſomevvhat Weſt, holding our courſe Eaſt
Northeaſt.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">They ſaw a man of war</note>The 9. of Augſt
vve entered the heades, and paſt them vvith a Southvveſt vvind, ſayling
Northeaſt. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter noone we paſt by a man of vvarre being a
<hi>Hollander,</hi> that lay at anker, and hee hoyſed anker to follow vs,
a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout euening vvee ſpake with him, but becauſe of the wind wee coulde
hardly heare what hee ſid, yet hee ſailed on with vs.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The man of war gaue them victu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ailes.</note>The
10. of Auguſt the man of warre borded vs with his boat, and brought vs a
barrell of Beere, ſome bread, and Cheeſe, ſhewing vs what news he could
touching the ſtate of <hi>Holland,</hi> and preſently wee ſawe the land
of <hi>Holland,</hi> &amp; becauſe it blew very ſtiffe &amp; a great
ſtorme, after noone wee ankered about <hi>Petten</hi> to ſtay for better
weather, and ſome new Pilots, &amp; that was the firſt time we had caſt
anker for the ſpace of 5. monthes together, about euening it beganne to blow
ſo ſtiffe, that wee loſt both an anker and a cable.</p>
            <p>The 11. of Auguſt we had ſtill a Southerly winde, &amp; 
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:9867:42"/> therefore about noone the <hi>Mauritius</hi> ſet
ſaile, and wee thought likewiſe to ſaile, but our men were ſo weake
that we could not hoyſe vp our anker, ſo that we were conſtrained to lie
ſtill till men came out to helpe vs, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout euening the winde came
Southweſt, and with ſo great a ſtorme, that we thought to haue run vpon
the ſtrand, 
<note place="margin">They cut down their main maſt.</note>and were
forced to cut downe our maine maſte.</p>
            <p>The 12. and <hi>13.</hi> we had a hard South weſt wind, &amp;
ſometimes Weſt, ſo that no Pilots came abord our ſhip, but the
<hi>13.</hi> day about euening it began to be faire wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>The 14. of Auguſt about breake of day in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, there came
two boats with Pilots and men abord our ſhip, that were ſent out by our
owners, &amp; brought vs ſome freſh victuailes, which done they hoyſed vp
our ankers, and about noone we ſayled into the <hi>Teſſel,</hi> and
ankered in the channell, where we had freſh victu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ailes enough, for we were
all very weake.</p>
            <p>This was a great noueltie to all the Marchantes and inhabitantes of
<hi>Hollande,</hi> for that wee went out from thence the ſecond of April
<hi>1595.</hi> and returned home a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain vpon the 14. of Auguſt <hi>1597.</hi>
there you might haue bought of the Pepper, Nutmegs, Cloues, and Mace, which
vvee brought vvith vs. Our ſaylors vvere moſt part ſicke, being but 80.
men in all, tvvo third partes of their company being dead, &amp; loſt by
diuers accidentes, and among thoſe foreſcore ſuch as vvere ſicke, as
ſoone as they vvere on land and at their eaſe preſently recoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red their
healthes.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <pb facs="tcp:9867:43"/>
            <div type="subsection">
               <head>The Copper money of Iaua.</head>
               <p> 
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>diagram of the copper coin of Java</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p>THis Copper money commeth alſo out of <hi>China,</hi> &amp; is
almoſt as thicke, great and heauy, as a quarter of a Doller, and ſomevvhat
thicker, in the middle hauing a ſquare hole, 2000. of them are vvorth a Riall
of 8. but of theſe there are not ouer many, the vſe to hang them vpon
ſtringes, and pay them without telling, they ſtand not ſo narrowly vpon
the number, for if they want but 25. or 50. it is nothing.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subsection">
               <head>The leaden money of Iaua.</head>
               <p> 
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>diagram of the lead coin of Java</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p>THis peece of money (being of bad Leade is very rough) hath in the
middle a foure ſquare hole, they are hanged by two hundred vppon a ſtring,
they are commonly <hi>10. 11.</hi> and <hi>12.</hi> thouſand to a Riall of 8.
as there commeth great quantitie out of <hi>Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> where they are made,
and ſo as there is plentie or ſcarcitie they riſe and fal.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:9867:43"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
